斯坦福大学
> Stanford University.
欢迎来到2013/14学年秋季CS193P课程第四讲
> Welcome to lecture 4, then, of CS 193P for fall of academic year 2013/14.
今天的内容几乎都将是幻灯片
Today I'm going to do pretty much all slides.
还有一点时间我们会简要看一个demo
I do have one brief time when we'll stop and do a little demo.
然后下一讲开始
And then at the beginning of next lecture,
我会讲一个demo 基本上演示了
I'll be doing a demo that pretty much demonstrates the vast
这一讲在幻灯中讲的大多数内容
majority of what I talk about in the slides today.
这将是这门课一贯的做法
And remember, that's kind of how it's always going to go:
我先讲一些幻灯片 然后用demo进行演示
I'll show it to you in slides, we'll talk about it, then I'll demo it to you.
因为看到demo比听老师一个劲在那讲
Because when you see a demo, it all makes a lot more sense than if someone's just talking
API相关的抽象概念要容易理解得多
in an abstract conceptually about an API.
然后作业通常是要你们做这个
And then your homework is usually going to ask you to do this.
你们需要在课上注意我都讲了什么
So it's, you know, you get a lot out of paying attention
因为这会为你们做作业提供很多提示
in the lectures because I'm pretty much going to give you hints
and basically tell you a lot of how to do the homework --
至少在iOS这方面
at least from the iOS side of it.
我还要求你们在意思考和设计这方面
I'm still going to ask you to do the thinking side of it, the designing side of it.
今天我们将首先谈到
So today we're going to start off by talking
Objective-C方面的各种知识
about a little bit more miscellaneous Objective-C.
然后我会讲到Foundation框架
And then I'm going to go into talking about Foundation,
也就是其中具有数组 字典等内容的框架
which is this framework that has arrays, and dictionaries, and all that in it.
最后我们会离开Foundation这一主题
And we'll start to transition out of Foundation at the end
并开始讨论字体 颜色等内容
of that and start talking about things like fonts and colors,
这些显然不属于Foundation
which are obviously not in Foundation
因为Foundation不是基于UI的
because Foundation is really not a UI-based thing;
它是用于构建模型 控制器 视图的
it's for building both your model, and your controller, and your view.
但它是用户界面层之下的一层
But it's, you know, a layer below the user interface layer.
我们开始进入主题
So let's dive right in.
我们先来看创建对象
Let's talk about creating objects.
希望这些东西是显而易见的
A few of these things are pretty obvious I hope, but I just want
这里我只是想把它们放到幻灯片中正式提一下
to put them on slides so that you have them in writing here.
大多数时候 当我们在堆中创建对象时
You know that most of the time when we create objects in the heap,
我们用的是alloc init 对吧
we do it with this alloc init business, right?
有时init是[NSMutableArray alloc] init中的init
So sometimes the init is just init like NSMutableArray alloc init,
有时 它更复杂 例如CardMatchingGame中的init
and sometimes it's more complicated init like we had with our card matching game --
initWithCardCount usingDeck
init with card count using deck --
你们需要熟悉这些
so that you're used to that.
你们还见过这种在堆中创建对象的方式
And you've also seen us create objects in the heap
使用类方法 例如stringWithFormat
using class methods like string with format.
记得吧 我们用过NSString stringWithFormat
Remember, we did NSString, string with format.
这是一个类方法
And that's a class method, right?
因为它是开方括号 类名 然后类方法
Because it's open square bracket, name of a class, and then class method.
这是两种你们见过的创建对象的不同方式
So it gets kind of two different ways you've seen already to create objects.
有时 对于一些方法
Sometimes for some methods,
同时有init和类方法
there's both an init and a class method.
stringWithFormat就是一个例子
So string with format is an example
这里有alloc initWithFormat
that there's alloc init with format
还有NSString stringWithFormat
and there's NSString, string with format.
它们的作用完全相同
They do exactly the same thing.
两者都在这里 可以说是一些历史原因
Both of them are there for kind of historical reasons.
在我们有这种自动引用计数之前
Back before we had this automatic reference counting --
这种强弱之类的东西
you know, the strong and weak thing --
你需要更加明确 何时引用事物
you had to be much more explicit about things when you were going to reference them,
何时取消引用 何时将它们从堆中清除 等等
and when they got dereferenced, and when you cleared them out of the heap, and all that stuff.
其中一种方式就是使用这些类方法
And one of the ways that was done was using these class methods
来创建能够用特定方式释放的字符串
to create the string in a way that it would get released in certain ways.
所有这些现在都不再重要
So all of that doesn't matter anymore.
这样我们就同时有了这两者
So now we're kind of stuck with having both of these things.
在我看来 苹果的iOS设计者们
It seems to me that iOS, the designers at Apple --
顺便说下 我不为苹果工作
I don't work at Apple, by the way.
有人问过我 我不在苹果工作
Some people have asked me if I work at Apple; I don't work at Apple.
我和你们一样 是从外部去看iOS的
So I'm just seeing iOS from the outside just like you are.
在我看来 iOS的人越来越偏向于alloc init
It looks to me like iOS people are moving towards alloc init,
逐渐从类方法偏离
okay, and kind of away from the class methods.
不过在特定环境下 我仍然会看到类方法
Although I still see the class methods coming up in certain circumstances, too.
这方面也许存在某种考虑
And there's probably some reasoning behind it.
我没看到过苹果官方说偏好哪一种
I haven't seen it put in writing by Apple as to when they choose which,
不过这门课的过程中 你们随便用哪种都是安全的
but you're certainly safe in this class until they start marketing some of these things
苹果应该不会在这么短的时间内决定废掉哪种
as deprecated, like, don't use them anymore, to use either form.
我多数时候更偏爱alloc init
I tend to try to go for the alloc inits most of the time,
除非没有alloc init能实现我的目的
unless there isn't an alloc init that does what I want;
这时我就会用类方法
then I'll use a class method.
不过还有其它方式可以创建对象
But there's other ways to create objects.
你可以让另一个对象为你创建对象
You can create objects by asking another object to create an object for you.
例如stringByAppendingString
So that's like string by appending string.
这不是字符串的类方法 这是实例方法
That's not a class method in string; that's an instance method.
你将它发送给一个字符串 你将它给第二个字符串
You send it to another string, you give it a second string,
它会为你创建一个新字符串 因为字符串是不可变的
and it will create a new string for you since strings are immutable.
NSString是不可变的
NSString is immutable.
它会创建一个新字符串
It creates a new string
这是将参数中的字符串加到原字符串后面
that is the string you sent it to with the one you passed as an argument added on, right?
这就为你创建了一个新对象
So there it's creating a new object for you.
一个很有趣的实例方法
And a very interesting instance method
你可以让对象为你做的
that you can ask an object to do for you
是mutableCopy(可变复制)
is mutable copy.
mutableCopy会复制一个对象 但它是可变的
So mutable copy makes a copy of an object but it's mutable.
例如将NSString发送给mutableCopy
So if you had an NSString and you send it mutable copy,
你会得到NSMutableString
you'll get back an NSMutableString.
或者将NSArray发送给mutableCopy
Or if you have an NSArray and you send it a mutable copy,
你会得到一个NSMutableArray
you'll get an NSMutableArray.
这是创建对象的另一种方式
So that's another way that that happens that you're creating objects.
当然 并非所有返回对象的方法都会创建一个对象
Of course, not all methods that return an object are creating an object
例如NSArray中的lastObject firstObject
like we saw in NSArray -- last object, and first object,
以及objectAtIndex
and object at index.
这些没有创建新对象
Those aren't creating new objects;
它们只是给你指针指向数组中的这些对象
they're just giving you pointers to the objects that are in those array.
这对你们而言应该很明显
That should be completely obvious to you
不过我这里想明确一下 这些是指向对象的指针
but I just want to make it clear, you know, these are pointers to objects.
你可以有多个指针
And you're allowed to have multiple pointers.
这里是普通的指针被来回传递
And this is normal pointers here being passed around.
除非方法中有copy这个单词
So basically, unless a method has the word "copy"
否则当方法返回给你一个已经存在的对象时
in it, then if it's returning to you an object that exists somewhere else,
它会返回指向那个对象的指针
it's going to be returning a pointer to that object,
除非方法中有copy这个词
okay, unless it has the word "copy" in it like
例如mutableCopy或copy
"mutable copy" or "copy."
如果你要返回的对象并不存在
And if the object that you're getting back doesn't exist
它就会为你创建新的对象
somewhere, then it's going to make a new one for you.
好 这是创建对象 非常简单
All right. That's it on creating objects. Pretty straightforward there.
nil 我已经讲过了
Okay. Nil, I already talked about this,
我们可以通过为nil的指针发送消息
that we can send messages through a pointer that is nil,
也就是说该指针不指向任何东西
i.e. that pointer does not point to anything.
没有代码会被执行
And no code gets executed.
如果我写
So if I do this
int i = [obj methodWhichReturnsAnInt]
init I equals obj method which returns an init,
没有代码执行到methodWhichReturnsAnInt
no code gets executed to execute method which returns an init;
但是
however,
发送方括号这些的消息会返回0
that message sending square bracket thing will return zero.
知道这个很重要
So that's important to know.
0也就是nil
And zero is also what nil is.
如果你的方法返回一个对象
So if you had a method that returned an object and you sent
你将那个消息发给nil 返回的也会是nil
that message to nil, then you get back nil.
这可以用来帮助我们达到一些目的
And we can use that, actually, to our advantage.
例如周一我们需要随机抽取纸牌 我们用了
For example, in our thing we did on Monday, we did draw a random card, right?
self.deck drawRandomCard
Self.deck draw random card.
如果牌堆里牌用完了 这会返回nil
And that returned nil if the deck was out of cards.
如果牌堆本身是nil 这也会返回nil
If the deck itself had been nil, that also would return nil.
这样我们就可以只写一个if
So we can write one if that deals with the fact
来处理抽不到牌的情况
that we can't get another card, whether it's
不管是因为牌堆空了 还是因为牌堆本就为nil
because the deck is empty or because there is no deck because the deck is nil.
两种情况下 代码的执行都一样
Either way, the code's going to look exactly the same.
你们会习惯这个的
So you'll get used to that.
这显然同其它语言有所不同
It's definitely different from other languages
其它语言中 你显然不希望将消息发送给nil
where you're protecting against sending messages to nil.
但你们会习惯的
But you'll get used to it.
你们确实需要小心 消息发送返回类型是struct的情况
You do have to be careful. If the return type of a message send is a struct
因为你无法得到所有成员都设为0的struct
because you don't get back a struct with all its members set to zero;
你得到的是一个未定义的struct
you get back an undefined struct.
其中有什么是未定义的
What's in there is undefined.
struct在栈上返回给你
This struct is being returned to you on the stack.
你可能得到栈垃圾
You might get stack garbage,
你可能得到0.struct 你无法知道
you might get zero.struct, you just don't know.
你不能依赖它
So you can't rely on it.
这里 代码中永远不要依赖这个
So here you should never rely on that in your code.
如果你调用一个返回struct的方法
If you call a method, it returns a struct,
你要检验 确保没有将它发送给nil
you got to check to make sure you're not sending it to nil.
好 动态绑定
All right. Dynamic binding.
Objective-C对方法分派和调用的处理
So Objective-C handles the dispatching and calling of methods
不同于你们大多数人所熟悉的语言
differently than languages that most of you are used to.
它所做的是动态绑定
It does what's called "dynamic binding."
通过这张幻灯片的讲解 你们会知道动态绑定是什么
And you'll see what dynamic binding is as we go through this slide.
Objective-C动态绑定很重要的一点在于
But the important thing to understand about dynamic binding and about Objective-C is
Objective-C中有一个非常非常重要的类型叫id
that there's a really, really important type in Objective-C called "ID," okay?
我们将它读作I-D 而不是id
We call it "ID." We don't call it id by the way; ID we call it.
代码中我会说 id myObject
So here in that line of code I would say that's ID my object.
这里声明了一个指针 我的对象 类型为id
So I'm declaring a pointer, my object, which is a type ID.
id是一个指针
So ID means pointer -- ID is a pointer,
所以不需要id
so we don't use ID star;
id就是指针
ID is a pointer --
它是一个指针 指向类未知的对象
it means a pointer to an object where I don't know its class.
指向未知类型或未指定类型
Of unknown type or unspecified type.
这是指向对象的指针
So it's just a pointer to an object;
我对对象则一无所知
I do not know anything about that object.
实际上 Objective-C中的所有指针都是id
Really, all pointers in Objective-C are IDs
当你将消息发送给一个对象时
in that the decision about what code to execute
关于执行什么代码的决定
when you send a message to an object is not determined
直到运行时才会决定
until runtime when you send that message.
当你发送一个消息时
When you send a message,
一个函数会被调用
it's essentially calling a function that's looking
查阅消息发送时 对应于所指向的那一特定类
up the right code to execute for that particular class
所应执行的正确代码
that you're pointing to at the time you send the message.
这被叫作动态或迟绑定
That's called dynamic or late binding.
Objective-C中的所有消息发送都是这样做的
And all message sends -- all of them in Objective-C -- are done this way.
这意味着什么呢
Now, what does this mean?
这意味着… 先看这安全吗
It means that -- well, is this safe, right?
因为你肯定会担心
Because you're worried, I'm sure,
我将消息发送给一个对象 如果它不理解该怎么办
"What if I send a message to an object and it doesn't understand it?"
没有机制能够阻止你这样做
Okay. Well, nothing stops you from doing that.
不仅如此 如果你这样做 程序就会崩溃
And not only that, if you do that, your program will crash.
这会引发异常
It will raise an exception.
除非捕获异常 否则程序会崩溃
Unless you catch the exception, it will crash.
你心里可能会想 哇
And so you're probably feeling like, "Wow.
这些Objective-C程序肯定总在崩溃
These Objective-C programs must be crashing all the time
因为一不小心就容易将消息发送给
because you accidentally send a message to an object;
不理解消息的对象
it doesn't understand that message."
但实际不是这样
But actually, it doesn't happen.
为什么没有发生呢
Okay. Why doesn't that happen?
原因有两点
And there's really two reasons.
一是我们经常使用静态类型化
One is we use static typing a lot.
我们不经常使用id
We don't use ID that much.
我们使用NSString *这些
We use, like, NSString star.
NSString *完全等同于使用id
Now, NSString star is exactly the same as using ID,
只是编译器在编译你的代码时
except that the compiler, while it's compiling your code,
知道你至少是意图让该指针指向一个字符串
knows that you at least intend that that pointer points to a string.
如果你尝试发送非字符串消息给该指针 它会抱怨
So if you tried to send a nonstring message to that pointer, it's going to complain.
它会给你警告
It's going to, you know, give you warnings.
所以在编译Objective-C程序时 你应确保没有警告
And so when you compile your Objective-C programs they should always have no warnings,
这样你就能够确保没有这种问题了
and then you can be pretty sure that you're not going to have this problem
没有在运行时将消息
where you send a message to an object at runtime
发送给一个不理解它的对象 从而导致崩溃
and it doesn't understand it and it crashes.
这是第一种方式
So that's the number one way.
我要讲的第二种方式是
And the second way I'm going to talk about
很多时候 在运行时我们都会检验
is that a lot of times we will check at runtime.
我们会看这个id指针
We'll look at that ID pointer.
在发送之前 我们会检验它是否能够正确作出反应
And we will check and see if it responds to something before we send it.
你们知道静态类型化
So you know about static typing,
也就是NSString *s = @"x"
that's the NSString star S equals at sign X.
这是非常安全 非常好的做法
This is really safe, really good,
任何糟糕的事情都不会发生在这里
nothing bad's going to happen here
因为编译器在编译时很好地知道你想要什么
because the compiler at compile time has a pretty good idea what you intend
如果不是 它会警告你
and it will warn you if not.
但是 编译器没有绑定这时执行的代码
However, the compiler is not doing the binding between what codes executes at this time;
它只是警告你 这是语法上的甜头
it's just warning you. It's syntactic sugar.
这种语法 它能看到并警告你
It's syntax that it can look at to warn you,
但这里没有任何强制作用
but it's not actually enforcing anything here.
用id obj =s也完全合法
It's perfectly legal to say ID obj equals S,
s也就是之前的s
where S is the line before.
这里就连警告都不会产生了
And that will not even generate a warning.
因为id obj是指向任何对象的指针
Because ID obj is a pointer to any kind of object;
s是指向任何对象的指针
S is a pointer to any kind of object.
根据前一行 它是一个指向字符串的指针
It's a pointer to a string, according to the previous line.
但由于两者都是指向对象的指针 这完全合法
But since those are both pointers to objects, that's perfectly legal.
编译器不会警告你
Compiler will not warn you.
这一行代码就有些危险了
This is a little bit of a dangerous line of code, right?
因为之前 s是类型化良好的变量
Because you just went from having S -- this nice variable that's typed
如果你做了不正确的事 编译器会告诉你
and the compiler can warn you if you do the wrong thing --
而obj是没有类型化的指针
to having an obj, which is this untyped pointer
不管发送什么消息 编译器都不会警告你
where you can send any message you want and the compiler's not going to warn you.
你还可以这样 NSArray *a = obj
You can also do this NSArray star A equals obj.
这时你就让NSArray变量指向了一个字符串
Okay. Now you have NSArray variable that points to a string.
这很可能会导致问题
Now, that's extremely likely to cause a problem.
这也是合法的
This is also legal
因为NSArray *a是一个指向对象的指针
because NSArray star A is a pointer to an object;
obj也是一个指向对象的指针 所以这样赋值是允许的
obj is a pointer to an object, so it allows this assignment.
非常危险 而且明显错误
Very dangerous. Obviously wrong.
这三行代码放到一起 显然是错误的
If these three lines of code are there, that's clearly wrong.
你不应当让NSArray指向NSString
You would not want to have an NSArray pointing to an NSString.
id在这方面可能会非常危险
So ID can be dangerous in this way.
实际上 我们在原来写的代码中也默默地做过这个
And in fact, in the code that we've written we already did this kind of silently.
在PlayingCard的match中
Remember that in match, playing card's match
我们有一行代码是
we put a line in there that said, "Playing
PlayingCard *otherCard = [otherCards firstObject]
card star other car equals other card's first object."
记得这个吗
Remember that?
NSArray中的firstObject方法返回一个id
Well, the method first object in an NSArray returns an ID.
你可以去查说明文档
If you go look it up in the documentation,
其返回类型 括号id
look at its return type -- parenthesis ID.
所以 我们将一个PlayingCard赋值给一个id
So we just assigned a playing card to an ID.
所以 从数组中得到的对象最好是PlayingCard
So that object that came out of that array better be a playing card
否则运行时就会崩溃
or we're going to crash at runtime.
这堂课晚些时候
And a little later in this lecture I'm going
我会讲到 如何保护代码 确保这种情况下不会崩溃
to show you how we can protect our code to make sure that we don't crash in this case.
大家都明白为什么说这里有点危险了吗
Does everyone see why this is a little dangerous?
这方面有问题吗
Questions about that?
好 提醒一下 绝对不要用id
Okay. And a reminder: Never use ID star.
id *没有意义 因为id就是指针
ID star makes no sense because ID is a pointer.
id *将是指向指针的指针
So ID star would be a pointer to a pointer.
我们在Objective-C中不会这样做
We don't do that in Objective-C, okay,
特别是指向id的指针
especially a pointer to an ID [inaudible].
为了总结上述内容 我将展示这个小小的例子
All right. So to summarize all this I'm going to show you this example.
我有两个类 一个Vehicle(交通工具)类
I've got two classes: I got a vehicle class,
它有一个方法move(运动) 交通工具可以运动
which has what method move -- you can move the vehicle around --
然后有Ship(船)类 它是一种交通工具
and I got a ship which is a vehicle,
继承自Vehicle
inherits from vehicle,
它只有一个方法 shoot(射击)
and it's only got one method, shoot.
这条船可以射击别的船
So this ship can shoot other ships.
它也能运动 因为它是交通工具
And they can also move because they're vehicles.
如果我声明一个局部变量 一条船s
So if I declare a local variable ship, ship S,
类型是Ship * 我用alloc init分配初始化一条船
which is a ship star, and I allocate init a ship,
我可以说s shoot或s move 都能行
I can say "S shoot" or "S move" -- works fine, right?
因为Ship实现了shoot 继承了move
Because ships implement shoot and they inherit move.
所以大家都相安无事
So everybody's totally happy here.
我还可以写 Vehicle *v = s 这完全合法
I can also do vehicle star V equals S. That's perfectly legal
因为v是一个交通工具 s也是一个交通工具
because V is a vehicle and S is a vehicle
因为它从船中继承了交通工具的性质
because it inherits its vehicle-ness from ship.
这有点像deck = [[PlayingCardDeck alloc] init]
Okay. This is like deck equals playing card deck alloc init --
这是程序运行中完全合法的对象
perfectly legal object to run in your programming, right?
下面我们尝试说 v shoot
Okay. But now let's try to say V shoot.
这里会发生什么
Now, what's going to happen here?
在编译时 你会得到警告
All right. At compile time you're going to get a warning
因为交通工具没有实现shoot
because vehicles do not implement shoot;
船有 但交通工具没有
ships do but not vehicles.
明白这里为什么会有警告了吗
So do you see why this is going to give you a warning?
运行时呢
What about at runtime?
这段代码不会崩溃
This code will not crash
因为我们知道v实际上是一条船
because we know that V actually is a ship.
所以这在运行时会运行得很好
So this will work fine at runtime.
明白了吗
Okay? See that?
这种情况下 编译时出现警告 到运行时运行得很好
So this is where you get a warning at compile time; runs fine at runtime.
这种情况呢 我声明一个obj
Now, what about this case where I declare an obj, okay,
它可以是任何东西
and it can be anything we want.
设法对它alloc init 然后写代码obj shoot
Alloc init it somehow and you say "obj shoot," okay?
不管obj是什么
No matter what obj is --
我故意没有讲清楚obj是什么
and I intentionally didn't tell you what obj
因为不管obj是什么
is because it doesn't matter what obj is.
编译器在这里都不会警告你
The compiler is not going to warn you here.
任何时候将消息发送给obj
Anytime you send a message to obj,
只要消息存在 编译器都不会警告你
as long as that message exists somewhere, the compiler will not warn you.
运行时 obj不是船或其它能对shoot作出反应的对象
At runtime, if obj is not a ship or some other object that responds to shoot,
程序就会崩溃
it will crash.
有问题
Question?
学生：id在这方面很特殊吗
> Is ID special in that way?
老师：哪方面
> In what way?
学生：因为似乎在这种情况下
> Because it seems like it's a similar case where
不管你怎么对obj赋值 它是指向对象的指针
whatever you've assigned obj is a pointer to an object
但它可能 也可能不具有这种方法
but it may or may not have this method.
老师：问题是 id在这方面很特殊吗
> Well, so the question is: Is ID special in that way?
你是说 id特殊在我可以发送任何消息给它
You mean is ID special in that I can send it any message I want
而编译器不会警告我
and the compiler won't warn me?
对 这就是id的语义
Yes. Because that's kind of the semantics of ID.
id是一个指针 指向类未知的对象
ID means a pointer to some object I don't know the class of.
所以编译器没法给你警告
So there's no way for the compiler to give you a warning.
它只会假设 有人会对shoot作出反应
So it just assumes "Okay, somebody responds to shoot.
也许是这个 我不会警告你
So it might be this one, so I'm not going to warn you."
确实 id在这方面很特殊
So yeah, ID is special in that way, I guess.
这就是我们不像这样单纯使用id的原因
That's why we don't want to use ID unadorned like this.
如果我说 obj 某不存在的方法名
If I'd say obj some method name that doesn't exist,
它确实会警告我
then it will warn me.
如果任何地方都找不到这个方法
So if it can't find that method anywhere,
编译器所知道的任何对象都没实现这种方法
no object that the compiler's ever heard of implements that method,
那它肯定会警告你
then it will at least warn you.
因为这时你很有可能是敲错了 犯了语法错误
Because then it's likely you had a syntax error. You mistyped it.
这时编译器就会帮你
And so the compiler is going to help you there.
假设我有一个NSString *hello
So let's say I had an NSString star hello.
我让它等于@"hello"
And I'm going to make it equal to at sign hello.
如果我说 hello shoot
If I say hello shoot,
编译器显然会警告我说
the compiler's obviously going to warn me and say,
字符串不会对shoot作出反应
"Strings don't respond to shoot."
而运行时 这会崩溃
And at runtime this would crash
因为字符串不会对shoot作出反应
because, of course, strings don't respond to shoot.
这很好 我们就希望情况是这样
Okay, so this is all good. This is the way we want things.
如果这样做呢 Ship *helloShip =
What if I did this, ship star hello ship equals
类型转换
cast --
大家都知道类型转换吧
okay, everyone knows about casting, right,
所有语言几乎都有类型转换
all languages have casting pretty much; well, most languages that you know --
(Ship *)hello
parenthesis ship star hello.
这完全是合法的 编译器也不会警告我
This is perfectly legal. And the compiler will not warn me.
我这里是将字符串放到了Ship *指针中
So I've now taken a string and put it in a ship star pointer.
这时编译器会认为helloShip是一条船
And the compiler now thinks that that hello ship is a ship.
它只会在看到船没有的方法时才会抱怨
And so it's only going to complain if you do things to it that don't look like ship,
虽然这里我们知道 这里是一个字符串
even though we know we know that that is a string.
所以说 类型转换极度危险
Okay. So casting can be super dangerous,
就像所有语言中一样
just like in any language casting can be dangerous.
这里也很危险
It can be dangerous here.
但我们有时会进行类型转换
But we do do cast sometimes.
我们使用类型转换的时候
And the times we cast are the
也就是我们使用id并加以保护的时候
same kind of times we use ID, which is protected times.
下一张幻灯片中我会讲到这种保护
I'm going talk about that protection on the next slide.
如果我们之后说 helloShip shoot
So if we then said hello ship shoot, okay,
这不会造成编译错误
that would not generate a compiling error
因为helloShip是一个Ship
because hello ship is a ship star;
但它在运行时会崩溃
however, it would crash at runtime
因为字符串不会对shoot作出反应
because strings don't respond to shoot.
都明白了吗
Everybody cool?
请讲
Yeah?
类型转换什么都没做 只是把编译器糊弄了
Okay, the typecasting really doesn't do anything; that is just tricking the compiler.
它其实没有执行任何代码
That's not even executing really any code per se.
当你发送shoot时 它会尝试分派那个shoot
It's when you send the shoot, it tries to dispatch that shoot
到那个helloShip变量
to that variable, that hello ship variable.
结果这玩意是字符串 于是崩溃掉
The thing turns out to be a string, and it crashes right there.
你还可以这样做 (id)hello shoot
You can also do this: ID hello shoot.
hello是NSString
So hello is the NSString star,
我将它转化为id 并将它发送给shoot
and I casted it to ID and sent it shoot.
这也会抑制所有警告信息
And that will suppress all warnings as well
因为我将shoot发送给一个id
because now I'm sending shoot to an ID.
我只是想说 一行之内就能类型转换
And I just want to show you here that you can cast it right in line;
无需创建新变量
you don't have to create another variable.
在一行内进行类型转换 会骗过编译器
If you cast it right in line, you fake out the compiler.
我们不希望骗过编译器
Now, we don't want to be faking out the compiler.
编译器是我们的朋友 它能帮我们找bug
Compiler is our friend. It helps us find bugs.
但这些都能够做到
But this all can be done.
这里讲这些东西
Mostly I put this up here to see the difference
我只是想讲清楚什么时候编译器能捕捉到
between the compiler catching something and it crashing at runtime,
以及什么时候会在运行时崩溃
okay, and when it does which.
好 我们什么时候会用到这种危险得荒唐的id呢
All right. So when would we ever use this ridiculously dangerous thing of ID?
之前其实有人问过 NSArray中
Well, someone asked earlier, "Can I have an NSArray
能否有不同种类的事物
that has different kinds of things in it --
一些字符串 一些数字 一些别的
some strings, some numbers, something else?"
当然可以
Absolutely you can.
而且很多时候 你确实想要这样做
And there's plenty of times when you absolutely want that.
这是很好的
So it's great for that.
Java等其它语言 会让你告诉编译器
Now, other language like Java lets you actually tell the
这个数组中有字符串
compiler that this array has strings in it
让编译器在你取出对象时
so that the compiler, when you pull objects out,
知道有什么类型 然后它来帮你
it knows what type they are and it can kind of help you out.
Objective-C不是这样
Objective-C doesn't have that.
编译器不会帮你处理数组内容
So the compiler cannot help you with contents array.
这是你的责任
So it's kind of your responsibility.
我会讲怎么处理这个的
I'm going to show you how we deal with that.
第二点是 记得MVC的内容吗
The second one is -- remember the MVC talk?
我讲了这种盲的结构化通信
I talked about all this blind structured communication, right, this blind communication.
要有这种盲通信
Well, to have blind communication you got
你需要有指针指向类型未知的对象
to have pointers to objects of types you don't know.
视图要将目标动作这些发送给
There's no way that the view can send the target action
不知道是什么类的控制器
thing to the controller without knowing the class of the controller,
视图就必须有某种指针
unless the view can have some kind of pointer
指向它不知道类型的控制器
to a controller that it doesn't know the type of.
这是id的一大用途
And that's big use of ID.
但是 我们需要保护我们自己
However, we need to protect ourselves,
id方面 我们有两大方法来保护自己
and there's two big ways that we protect ourselves against IDs.
一是内省
One is introspection,
过几张幻灯片我就会讲到
which I'm going to talk about in the next few slides,
也就是我们可以在运行时问一个id 你是什么类的
which is we can ask an ID at runtime, "What class are you?"
或你对什么方法作出反应
or "What methods do you respond to?"
这是一种很棒的保护方式
So that's a great way to protect ourselves.
另一种方式叫作协议
And then another way is called "protocols."
协议是在id后使用尖括号来表示
And protocols is a way using little angle brackets after an ID to say,
这是一个id 一个指针 指向的对象我不知道类是什么
"This is an ID, a pointer to some class I don't know what it is,
但它要能对尖括号中定义的这一组方法作出反应
but it responds to this set of methods that I'm going to
define with this little angle bracket thing
如UIScrollViewDelegate
like UI scroll view delegate."
这就是我们进行委托和数据源这些的方式
And that's how we do the delegation and data source thing.
今天我们不会过多讲到协议 因为这里不大需要
So we're not going to talk about protocols today because you don't quite need them.
我们也许会在下周或下下周讲到它
We'll probably talk about them next week or the week after.
这是我们在id上保护自己的另一方式
But that's another way we protect ourselves against ID
id后跟尖括号实际上介于纯id和静态类型之间
by having like -- an ID with the angle brackets is kind of in
id后跟尖括号实际上介于纯id和静态类型化之间
between pure ID and static typing. It's kind of in the middle, right?
这里静态类型化的不是类型
Instead of static typing the type,
而是事物能够对其作出反应的消息
we're just static typing the messages that the thing can respond to.
就安全而言 它可以说介于中间
So it's kind of in the middle in terms of safety.
好 我们再来讲内省
So let's talk about introspection, though.
NSObject中有一些内省方法
There's a few introspection methods in NSObject.
这里我要讲三个
I'm going to talk about three of them here.
isKindOfClass isMemberOfClass
Is kind of class, is member of class,
以及respondsToSelector
and responds to selector.
isKindOfClass及isMemberOfClass
So is kind of class and is member of class
让你能够问一个NSObject
lets you ask an NSObject
或者任何继承自NSObject的对象
or anything that inherits from NSObject,
你属于这一系列类吗
"Are you of this kind of class?
或者isMemberOfClass是说
Or is member of class means,
你实际是这个类吗
"Are you actually this class?"
不是这个类及它的子类 而是只包含这个类
Not this class or something that inherits from it, but actually this actual class.
respondsToSelector说的则是 id指向的这一对象
And then response to selector says, "Does this object that this ID points to,
是否对某一特定方法作出反应
does it respond to a certain method?"
很不幸 这些方法的参数显得很不牢靠
So the arguments unfortunately to these methods are really kind of wonky.
这些你们使用的时候照做即可
And just you're going to have to take my word for it on these ones
因为等下我要用来解释这个的句子里
because when I spit out the sentence in a second here that describes what the argument is,
会使用四次class(类)这个词
I'm going to use the word "class" four times
每次都表示不同事物
and it's going to mean four different things.
isKindOfClass的参数
So the argument is kind of class,
是通过将类方法class发送到某一个类来得到
you get by sending the class method class to the class,
这会给你一个大写C开头的Class
which will give you a capital C Class,
这就是isKindOfClass的参数
which is the argument to the is kind of class method.
这里有一个方法class
So there's this method class.
在这里 NSString class
You see it there, NSString class.
它是一个NSString的类方法 返回Class
It's a class method on NSString returns a capital C Class.
这是isKindOfClass的参数
And that's the thing that's the argument is kind of class.
它总是这样的形式 [obj isKindOfClass:
It's always of this form, obj is kind of class,
[你要考虑的类 class]]
open spare bracket, the class you want, class, close square bracket, closed square bracket.
它总是这样 照做就行了
So it always looks like this. So just do it.
如果你不能理解句子中包含四个class的解释
If you didn't understand my four-class sentence,
别管它 照做就行了
just do it just like this.
发现对象属于这一系列类后 就可以进行类型转换了
Once I see that an object kind of a class, then I might want to cast it.
注意这里我将obj转换为NSString *类型
You see here I'm casting obj to be an NSString star there
因为我知道这时 它是NSString
because I know at that point it's an NSString star.
所以这时愚弄编译器没有关系
So it's okay to fool the compiler,
或者说 我是通过这样在教编译器更多关于obj的知识
or really I'm teaching the compiler a little bit more about what obj is by doing that.
并非真的愚弄它
Not really tricking it.
这样做是完全安全的 因为我知道obj
And it's perfectly safe to do that because I know that obj
在运行时是这样的类
at runtime is that kind of class.
这方面有问题吗 请讲
Questions about that? Yeah?
问题是 实例方法class会怎样 我可以说
Okay, the question is: What does the instance method class -- so I can say, you know,
想象一个例子 例如我们用过的deck
trying to think of an example where we use that, like deck.
我可以说deck class
I might say deck class, for example.
这会返回同这里基本一样的东西
That returns essentially the same thing as here,
你也许可以说
and you probably could say
isKindOfClass 开方括号 实例方法class
is kind of class open square bracket instance method class.
但你的读者会对此非常不解
But your reader would pretty darn confused by that.
这里有实例方法和类方法 我想都返回相同的东西
So there's an instance method and a class method; probably both return the same thing,
大写C的Class
capital C class, I believe.
但我们这里不会这样做 不要在这里调用实例方法
But we would never do that here, so don't put an instance call there,
仅使用类方法
just the class method you want.
问得很好
Good question.
再来看方法的情况
All right. How about the selector one, the method one rather?
这类函数对选择某事物作出反应时所使用的
Okay. So methods, when we use them in this response to select a thing,
叫作selector(选择器)
we call them "selectors."
selector可以说是一个方法名的识别器
A selector is really kind of an identifier for a method name
以方法shoot为例
because if you have the method shoot,
不管你考虑哪种实现它的类 selector都是一样的
it's the same selector no matter what class you're talking about implementing it in.
哪怕它们之间没有继承关系 完全无关
Even if they don't inherit from each other, they're completely unrelated.
例如一个Gun(枪)类拥有shoot方法
You might have a gun class that says shoot
还有一个Ship类拥有shoot方法
and you might have a ship class that says shoot --
shoot的selector是一样的
the selector shoot would be the same.
获得selector的方式是
And we get that selector by saying
用@selector(方法名)
at sign selector parenthesis, the name of the method.
例如shoot
Shoot.
如果方法有多个参数 我们只需将冒号加到这里
And if the method has multiple arguments, we just put the colons in there.
例如shootAt:有一个参数
So shoot at colon has one argument
或者addCard: atTop:
or add card colon at top colon.
我们只需要写
We just say that,
@selector(addCard: atTop:)
at sign selector, open parenthesis, add card colon, add top colon, close parenthesis.
这会给我们selector
And that gives us the selector,
然后我们说respondsToSelector
and we say responds to selector.
这会告诉我们
And that will tell us whether the
我们发送给respondsToSelector的对象
object that we're sending responds to selector
是否对此方法作出反应
to responds to that method.
这些selector实际上是一种类型
Now, these selectors, there's actually a type,
这些selector在Objective-C中是一种typedef
kind of a type def in Objective-C for these selectors.
全大写SEL 同全大写BOOL一样
All caps SEL, kind of like all caps BOOL, right?
这里加入了这种typedef
So this type def thing is added.
你可以声明类型为SEL的变量 并将事物存储于其中
And you can declare variables that are of type SEL and store things in there.
实际上还有respondsToSelector之外的其它方法
And there are actually other methods besides respond to selector
将selector作为参数
that take a selector.
例如 对象有performSelector:
For example, object has perform selector
以及performSelector:withObject:
and perform selector with object.
它们会将这一方法执行到另一个对象上
They will perform that method on another object.
为什么要这样做呢
Now, why would you ever want to do this?
因为你可能有一些参数化的东西
Well, you might have some parameterized thing
你要处理三种不同方法中的一个
where you're going to do one of three different methods,
取决于用户的选择
depending on something the user chooses.
你可以说performSelector
And you can say perform selector
然后有三个SEL变量 对应每种方法
and then have three SEL variables, one for each method,
将这作为performSelector的参数
and pass that as the argument you want to perform selector.
performSelector: withObject:
Perform selector with object,
这一方法有一个参数
that method would have one argument.
selector名应该是某某冒号
So the selector name better be something colon
因为它有一个参数
because it's got one argument.
而参数必须是一个对象
And the argument has to be an object.
coordinate在这里是某种对象
So coordinate here would be some sort of object.
这里有一点限制
So just a little limitation.
方法要么没有参数 要么有一个对象作为参数
It can only have no arguments or have one argument that's an object.
你还可以让数组做如下很酷的事
You can also do cool things like ask an array
让数组中所有对象执行这个selector
make all the objects in yourself perform this selector.
这是一个很酷的方法
This is a very cool method.
如果你能习惯在数组中使用这样的方法
And if you get used to using methods like this in Array,
你的代码量会大幅减少
you'll find your code will shrink down really small
因为for in循环这些
because, you know, for ins and things
会缩减为这样的一行代码
like that you have to really zoomed down to one-liners,
makeObjectsPerformSelector:
make objects perform selector, okay,
或makeObjectsPerformSelector: withObject:
or make object perform selector with object.
这是NSArray的方法
So that's an NSArray thing.
显然 我们还用selector处理目标动作
And of course, we do target action with selectors.
如果你想设置目标动作
The method, if you wanted to set up target action,
不用Control拖动 而是在代码中设置
not doing control drag but actually setting up in code,
方法在UIControl中 按钮就是继承自这里
is in UI control actually, which button inheritance from.
addTarget: action:
Add target colon, action colon.
还有其它一些参数
There's some other arguments.
不过addTarget:的参数是id类型
But you can see that add target takes an ID
然后action:的参数是selector
and then it takes an action colon, takes a selector.
它会说明 什么消息发送到什么对象
So it says what message to send to what object --
什么是目标 什么是动作
what's the target, what's the action?
大家都理解了吗
Everyone understand that?
这是选择
Okay. So this selection stuff,
selector非常强大
pretty selector stuff is pretty powerful.
下面我们来看match
All right. So let's take a look at how match --
PlayingCard中的match
the playing card match --
如何用内省来改善
might be improved with introspection.
我将回到Xcode
I'm going to go here back to Xcode.
打开之前我们编辑过的Machismo
And I'm just going to open back up Machismo where we left off here.
然后在下面找到PlayingCard
Okay. And then let's go down to playing card.
这是PlayingCard 这是match
So here's playing card and here's match.
都记得match吧
Okay. So you all remember match.
这一行代码有一点问题
And here's the line of code that's a little bit of trouble.
因为这里第一个对象 它会返回一个id
Because this first object here, this returns an ID.
所以我们可以这样做 id card = 这个
So what we could do here, for example, is we could say ID card equals this.
我要让这里完全清晰
Just to be totally clear here.
我得到了这个card 然后我说
So we got this card. And then I can say
if ([card isKindOfClass:[PlayingCard class]])
if card is kind of class, playing card class,
那么 我将做所有这些
okay, then I'll do all this.
而且我要将另外这张牌设为
And I'm going to set the other card here to be
(PlayingCard *)card
playing card, star card.
这里是类型转换
So I'm going to cast it.
这时编译器就知道了这个变量
So now the compiler knows about this variable.
从这里开始 当我触摸另一张牌时
And from here on out, whenever I touch other card,
它都会知道这张牌是PlayingCard
it knows it's going to be a playing card.
而这里 我在运行时检验 以保证它是PlayingCard
And here I've checked at runtime to make sure that it's actually the playing card
这样这里就永远不会崩溃
so that I'll never crash here.
如果你说 match:otherCards
Now, if you say match colon other cards
而otherCards不是PlayingCard(扑克牌)
and the other cards are like, some not playing cards,
例如只是普通卡片 或是字符串 这不会有问题
they're regular cards or they're strings or something, then that's okay.
这个方法能够运行
This method's going to work fine because it's going
因为它会返回0 分数为0 这是对的
to return zero, a score of zero, which is right
因为扑克牌不能同字符串或普通卡片匹配上
because a playing card wouldn't match a string or any other kind of card.
能理解吗
Make sense?
明白这里是如何使用内省的吗
See how we used introspection there?
你们将会在下周的作业中用到内省
So you will have to use introspection most likely in your solution to next week's homework --
不是现在你们在做的这次
not the one you're currently working on.
顺便我需要说明一下
By the way, I should take time out to say I'd almost --
我在课堂上讲的内容
if I ever show you something in a lecture
在我布置以后 这几乎从不需要用在当周的作业中
after I've assigned something to you, you almost never need it in that week's homework.
否则我会另行通知你们
And I would tell you if that were the case.
懂我说的吗
You know what I'm saying?
例如 周一布置的作业
So, like, you've got an assignment on Monday;
我不会今天讲一些东西 让你们用在周一的作业中
I wouldn't be showing you things today that you needed for the assignment on Monday.
布置作业时 这次作业所需的内容就已经都讲过了
I've already shown you everything you need by the time you get the assignment.
有问题
Question?
问题是 内省是不是只用于
Okay. So the question is: Is introspection only used
从数组中选出项目这样的时候
like this when you're pulling items out of Array?
记得吧 两张幻灯片前我讲了
And remember, I told you a couple slides ago
我们主要有两种时候用到内省 一是这个
there are two major times when we use introspection -- one is this.
二是所有MVC盲通信
Second one is all that MVC blind communication, right?
目标动作 委托等等那些
Target action, and delegation, and all that stuff.
这是这部分内容
So that's that.
下面转入Foundation
Now let's move onto Foundation.
这里我们要讨论Foundation框架
So we're going to talk about a Foundation framework here.
我将很快过一遍对象 数组 字典等等这些
I'm going to really go fast through object, Array, dictionary, things like that
因为我们已经见过很多数组
because we've already seen a lot of Array.
你们应该已经知道它是什么了
I think you pretty much got a good feel for what it is.
所以我不会花太多时间讲
So I don't want to waste the time talking about that.
我们有很多新东西要讲
We got a lot more new stuff to talk about.
你们知道NSObject是所有对象的基类
But you know that NSObject is the base class for all objects.
它实现内省这些东西
It implements those introspection things.
它还实现了这个很重要的方法
It also implements this very important method
叫作description(描述)
called description.
description会返回一个NSString
So description, it just returns an NSString.
它返回的字符串用于描绘这个对象
And it's supposed to return a string that describes this object.
什么时候用这个呢
When do we ever use this?
两个地方 一是NSLog
Two places. One, NS log.
调试时 我们喜欢用NSLog %@
When we're debugging, we like to NS log percent at sign.
用%@时
And when we do percent at sign,
description会被发送给匹配对象
the matching objects get sent description, and that's what gets sent out.
NSString通过返回self来实现description
Now, NSString implements a description by returning self.
NSObject对description的实现非常糟糕
NSObject implements description very badly.
它会返回指针
It returns like the pointer,
带有指针的字符串这之类
a string with the pointer in it or something.
在你自己的类中实现时 description会很有用
Description becomes valuable when you implement it in your own classes.
例如在PlayingCard中 你可以实现description
So you could imagine implementing in playing card,
甚至在Card中 你也可以实现description
or even in card you could implement description
返回self.contents
that would return self.contents.
然后在调试器中 你就能够…
And then in the debugger there's a way --
周五的课上你们会看到
in which you'll see this Friday's section --
你就能够在调试器中打印一个对象
there's a way to print an object in the debugger.
它会为你调用description 并返回它
It will call description for you and return it.
于是你就能看到纸牌的内容 这非常酷
So for card you'd see the contents. So that's really cool.
而字符串显示的是字符串
And the string shows you the string.
数组和字典实现description时
Arrays and dictionaries implement description
会打印出数组内容
to print out the contents of the array.
所以说description是NSObject中很酷的函数
So description's a really cool little function to know about in NSObject.
NSObject还实现了这种复制框架
NSObject kind of implements this framework for copying,
但它并没有实际实现copy和mutableCopy
but it doesn't actually implement copy and mutable copy.
查一下NSObject你就会知道
If you look in NSObject, you'll see that
这些方法在这里有一个协议
these methods are implemented there or there's a protocol for them there.
copy和mutableCopy
Copy and mutable copy are --
它们的语义在不同类中有所不同
the semantics of them vary from class to class.
其实现取决于类
So it's up the class to implement it.
不要被NSObject中的copy和mutableCopy糊弄到
Don't be fooled by the fact that copy and mutable copy are in NSObject.
不是将copy发送给任何对象就能复制的
You can't just send copy to any object and it will copy it.
但NSArray NSDictionary这些
But NSArray, for example, NSDictionary, these things,
实现了copy和mutableCopy
they implement copy and mutable copy,
它们做了正确的事情
and they do the right thing.
关于copy有一点要注意 如果将copy
One thing to note about copy is if you send copy
发送给一个可变对象 例如可变数组
to a mutable object like a mutable array,
返回的将不是可变数组
you don't get a mutable array back,
虽然你是在copy可变数组
even though you just copied a mutable array.
返回的却是不可变数组
You get an immutable array back.
copy的语义是
The semantics copy are,
如果可能 返回该对象的一个不可变副本
"Give me an immutable copy of this object back if possible."
mutableCopy的语义是
The semantics of mutable copy are,
返回该对象的一个可变副本
"Give me a mutable copy of this thing."
不管接收可变或不可变复制的是什么
No matter whether the receiver is mutable or immutable,
mutableCopy意味着返回可变副本
mutable copy means give me a mutable copy;
copy意味着返回不可变副本
copy means give me an immutable copy.
理解了吗
Understand that?
重申一次 特定类实现这个
And again, certain classes implement this;
NSObject则没有
NSObject really does not.
如果你希望自己的对象可复制 你需要自己实现
You would have to implement it yourself if you wanted to have your objects be copyable,
这非常罕见
which is pretty rare by the way.
一般不需要这样做
Really not generally doing that.
好 NSArray是对象的有序集合
Okay. NSArray is an ordered collection of objects.
它是不可变的
It's immutable.
NSArray一经创建 其中的对象就会一直保持不变
When you create an NSArray, whatever objects are in it
when you create it, those are the objects that will be in there for life.
无法删除 也无法添加任何对象
You can't remove any, you can't add any.
数组中所有对象在堆中都是强存储的
All objects in an array are held onto strongly in the heap.
只要该数组本身处在堆中
So as long as that array itself is in the heap, okay,
只要有强指针指向数组本身
as long as someone has a strong pointer to the array itself,
数组中的所有对象也都会留在堆中
all the objects that are in the array will stay in the heap as well
因为有强指针指向所有这些对象
because it has strong pointers to all of them.
NSArray的创建
You usually create an NSArray
有时会调用类方法 甚至调用alloc init
by sometimes calling a class method or even alloc init.
但最普遍的情况下 我们会使用@[]
But usually most commonly we do that at sign square bracket thing,
例如创建rank字符串时
like how we created rank strings.
记得吧 PlayingCard中的rank字符串
Remember rank strings in playing card,
@ 方括号 然后元素
at sign, square bracket, and the elements?
这就是通常创建数组的方式
That's usually how we create arrays.
有时我们创建数组是通过要其它数组
Sometimes we'll create arrays by asking other arrays
在自身上加一个对象 然后返回新数组
to add an object to themselves and give us a new array
因为这里不可变
since they can't be mutated;
所以必须生成新的并返回
they have to make a new one and give it back.
这是另一种方式
So that's another way.
你们知道基本的count objectAtIndex等方法
And you know the basic, you know, get the count, object at index.
数组中还有很多其它非常酷的方法
There's a lot of other really cool methods in an array.
这个类你们需要非常熟悉才行
You really should familiarize yourself with this class.
这里有很多东西
Okay. It's a lot of stuff.
我讲过makeObjectsPerform
We talked about make objects perform.
这里还有sortedArrayUsingSelector
There's sorted array using selector.
你可以给它一个selector
So you give it a selector that takes another --
它被发送到数组中的每个对象
that basically gets sent to each object in the array
并将数组中另一个对象作为参数
and takes one of the other objects in the array as an argument.
你要确保这里的参数类型正确
So you got to make sure they have the right type of argument there.
它会这样来创建一个排过序的数组
And it will just use that to create a sorted version of the array
并返回这个排过序的新数组
and give you back a new array that's sorted.
只要你有一个selector
Okay. So one line of code as long as you have a selector
针对一个方法 能够对比数组中的两个对象
for a method that can compare two objects that are in an array,
你就能够排序
you can sort it.
NSArray中的这些怪异内容你都需要知道
So you really should know about all these kind of whacky things in NSArray.
NSArray无法被修改
Now, NSArray can't be modified.
这有时存在局限
Sometimes that's a limitation,
但可能没你们想的那么严重
not as often as you might think.
当然 还有一种可变的数组
But there's a mutable version of Array, of course,
叫作NSMutableArray 这个我们也用过
called NSMutableArray, which we've also used.
我们通常使用alloc init来创建它
We usually create it using alloc init
有时我们则会使用arrayWithCapacity
or sometimes we use Array with capacity.
arrayWithCapacity中
Array with capacity is --
容量参数只是性能提示
that capacity argument is just performance hint.
它并没有说 数组最开始只能有那么多项目
It's not saying that the array starts out with that many items;
它只是说 我觉得这个数组中将有100个元素
it just means, "I think this array is going to have a hundred things in it."
创建100个元素的数组 这只是性能提示
So creating an array with a hundred -- it's a performance hint only.
你们知道NSMutableArray继承了NSArray的一切
You know that NSMutableArray inherits everything from NSArray,
当然 它还增加了addObject:
of course, and then it adds add object,
insertObject:
insert object at,
removeObject: atIndex:
remove object at index.
你们还知道 可以使用方括号表示法
And you know that you can use the square brackets notation,
例如 self.cards[index]
right, like self.cards open square bracket, index,
将事物放到数组中 或是从数组中删除
closed square brackets to both put things into an array and get things out of an array.
使用这种表示法其实也就是调用
And using that notation is really just calling
objectAtSubscriptedIndex
object at subscripted index
以及setObjectAtSubscriptedIndex
and set object at subscripted index.
这里不过是在调用这些方法
Okay. It's just calling those methods; that's all it's doing.
但使用方括号表示法让代码更清晰
But it looks really nice in your code to use those square brackets.
枚举 我们知道如何使用for in结构
Enumeration, we saw how to do this for in business.
不要忘记 控制变量
Don't forget that that control variable
例如NSString *string in myArray
like NSString star string in my array --
这里有NSString *string
you see the NSString star string --
这实际上是类型转换
that's essentially your casting.
你将该数组中取出的元素转化为NSString
You're casting, whatever comes out of that array to be an NSString.
你告诉编译器 我知道这个数组中都是字符串
You're telling the compiler, "I know that what's in that array is strings."
如果你不知道数组中都是什么
Now, if you don't know what's in there,
或者如果是混合事物
you could say -- or if it's a mixed things --
你可以说 for (id obj in myArray)
you would say for ID obj in my array.
这时 迭代变量将是obj
Then the iteration variable will be an obj
你可能需要内省来弄清
and you'll likely want to use introspection to find
每次经过循环时 返回给你的东西是什么
out what the thing you got back is each time around the loop.
能理解吗
Make sense?
下一个 NSNumber
Next NSNumber.
NSNumber这个类被用于包含原始类型
NSNumber is a class that is used to wrap primitive types
例如整型 浮点型 双精浮点型 布尔型等等
like integers, floats, doubles, Bools, things like that.
为什么要把这些总起来呢
And why do you want to wrap them?
通常是因为你想把它们放入数组或词典
Usually because you want to put them in Array or a dictionary.
你不能将int放到数组中 你需要NSNumber对象
So you can't put an int into an array; you need to have an NSNumber object.
你可以用类方法创建它们 例如numberWithInt
You can create them with class methods like number with int --
这是NSNumber方法中的一个类函数
that's a class number in a class method NSNumber --
你也可以使用@()
or you can use at sign parenthesis.
我们已经看到过@[]用于数组
So we already saw at sign square bracket for arrays,
这里还有@()
there's also at sign parenthesis,
甚至在创建数字时还可以用@数字
or even just at sign number if you want to create a number.
例如@3
So you could say at sign three.
还可以有@3.2
You could also say at sign 3.2,
这会创建一个NSNumber 包含这一原始类型
and that would create an NSNumber that would contain that primitive type.
如果使用括号 那么你就可以在括号中
If you put the parenthesis, then you could put things inside
调用返回原始类型的方法
like calls to methods that return a primitive type,
或枚举
or enums,
或任意你想放到这里的东西
or anything you want in there --
任意计算得到原始类型的表达式都能放到括号内
any expression that evaluates to a primitive type can be put inside of parenthesis.
你可以说@() 它会根据结果创建一个NSNumber
You say at sign parenthesis and it will create an NSNumber with the result.
大家都理解了这种语法吗
Everybody understand that syntax?
其它语言都有这种自动装箱
Okay. So other languages kind of have this autoboxing kind of stuff in there.
NSValue 我不打算讲太多
NSValue, I'm not going to talk too much about it.
这是一种封装比原始类型更复杂类型的方式
It's essentially a way to encapsulate more complicated types than primitive types,
基本上也就是C struct
so structs basically, C structs.
NSValue知道如何包装
And NSValue knows how to wrap up
iOS中一些不同类型的struct
a few different kinds of structs that are in iOS.
具体哪些你们可以参阅说明文档
And you can go look at the documentations to see which ones.
这里我要简单提到的是一点是
One thing I'm going to give you a little tip right here, okay,
有时将struct包装起来的好办法是将它转化为字符串
sometimes a good way to wrap up a struct is to turn it into a string.
然后你可以把它作为字符串放入数组
Then you can put it in the array as a string.
这很棒 可以在调试器中打印 可以很好地看到
It's nice because you print it out in the debugger and you can see it really nicely.
然后还有办法将字符串转换为C struct
And then there's ways to turn things from strings back into C structs.
iOS中有C函数能将大多数struct转化为字符串
So there are C functions in iOS that turn most of the structs in iOS into strings
还有其它C函数将字符串转化回struct
and then other C functions that turn the strings back into the structs.
NSValue… 我认为多数时候你们可以用字符串
So NSValue -- I think most of the time you can use strings.
也许存储在NSValue中更高效
It's probably more efficient to store something as an NSValue
不过还是那句话 不要过度优化
but, again, don't overoptimize.
转化为字符串在使用时也很不错
Turning into a string is just as performant in the case you're using it.
这是因为它是一个字符串 很容易处理
It's nice because it's a string and it's easy to look at.
NSData是另一种Foundation类
NSData is another Foundation class,
只是"二进制包"
just a bag of bits.
我们将使用NSData
And we're going to be using NSDatas.
以后讲到时我会进一步讲
We'll talk about them more when we get to that.
简单说来 NSData不过是一些二进制数据
But it's just basically a certain count of bytes, that's what NSData is.
NSDate是日期
NSDate is a date, right?
它有一些内部表示
It has some internal representation.
也许是UNIX表示
It's probably the UNIX representation
如1970年以来的秒数 诸如此类
like the number of seconds since 1970 or whatever it is.
NSDate可以这样考虑 如果你要在UI中加入日期
One thing to think about with NSDates, if you're going to put a date in your UI,
你需要知道你在做什么
you got to know what you're doing.
为什么呢
Why is that?
这是因为日期在世界范围内差异很大
That's because dates vary dramatically all around the world.
我讲的还不是在法国
And I'm not just talking about in French, you know,
连月份名字都不同 要知道
the month names are different, but you know,
甚至连月在前还是日在前 不同地方都会不同
the order of whether the month comes first or the date comes first varies.
世界上有些地方
Some places on earth,
使用的日历都跟我们不一样
some locales don't even use the same calendar as we use.
所以iOS中有大量基础设施来处理这个
So there is an enormous amount of infrastructure in iOS for dealing with this.
有NSCalendar这样的类
Classes like NSCalendar,
有日期格式化器等等
and date formatter, and things like that.
如果你要在UI中使用日期 请务必熟悉所有这些
If you're going to put in your UI, familiarize yourself with all of that.
课堂上我显然没时间一一讲解
I don't have time to go over it all in lecture unfortunately.
但你需要知道 有些东西你需要知道
But you just need to know that there's something you need to know.
你不能在UI中仅仅说NSDate description
You can't just say NSDate description and put it in the UI.
日期比这要复杂很多
Dates are a little bit complicated.
NSSet是对象的无序集合
There's NSSet, which a set is an unordered collection of objects,
对象都是唯一的
so the objects are unique.
就算你把相同对象放进去两次 它也只会存在一次
So you put the same objects in there twice, it only goes in there once.
NSSet就是一般意义上的集合
So sets are what you would think of in term of sets.
然后还有有序集 介于NSSet和数组之间
And there's actually an ordered set, which is like a cross between the set and an array.
你们可以自己去查
And you can look those up.
这些你们可能用不着 NSSet你们可能会用到
You're not going to need those probably -- well, you might need set.
NSSet很好
Set is nice because you can do things if you have --
很便于告诉你集合中是否有什么
set is very good at telling you whether something's in the set.
而数组 如果数组中有一千个元素
Whereas an array, if you had an array of a thousand things,
数组可能需要进行二分查找
the array might have to do some binary searching or --
二分查找可能都不行 因为它不知道顺序
well, I guess it can't even binary search because it doesn't know the order.
它会在这里面到处找 很难找到东西
So it's got to look around in there. It's hard for it to find things.
但NSSet经过了hash处理 效率很高
But a set is probably hashed and high efficiency.
就算集合中有一万个对象
It can tell you if you had a set of ten thousand objects
你问它 这个对象在里面吗
and you ask it, "Is this object in there?"
它会很高效地告诉你
it could probably tell you really efficiently.
有时NSSet对比数组还是有些价值的
So there are some values sometimes sets versus Array.
好 字典
Okay. Dictionary.
这是第二重要的集合类 可能仅次于数组
This is the second most important collection class behind Array probably.
它是键值对的不可变集合
It's an immutable collection of key value pairs.
类似hash表
It's like a hash table.
所有键和值都是强存储的
All the keys and values are held onto strongly.
如果它们在那里作为键或值 那么它们就在堆中
So if they're in there as a key or a value, then they're in the heap.
只要字典在堆中 它们就在
And they stay in there as long as the dictionary stays in the heap.
键和值显然都是对象
The keys and values, obviously, are both objects.
等下我会讲到键要怎样才能成为键
We'll talk about what the key has to do to be a key in a second here.
不可变NSDictionary的创建方法通常是
You usually create immutable NSDictionaries using another
另一种@语法 即@花括号
at sign syntax called "at sign curly brace."
形如@ 花括号 键:值 逗号
Okay. So it's at sign curly brace, key colon value, comma,
键:值 逗号 键:值 反花括号
key colon value, comma, key colon value, end curly brace.
这类似于数组的@[]
So this is kind of like the at sign square brackets
以及NSNumber的@()
for arrays or the at sign parenthesis for NSNumbers.
这是@版本的NSDictionary
This is NSDictionary's version of that.
你可以在字典中查东西
You look up things inside a dictionary.
显然你可以用objectForKey
You can obviously do object for key.
这是通过键找值的很好方法
That's a nice method for looking the value up by key.
但你也可以使用方括号
But you can also use square brackets
类似于在数组中查找
that looks kind of like looking up an array.
例如幻灯片中的这个颜色字典colors
So if I had that colors dictionary that's showing right there
字符串有绿 蓝 红
and I had a string that was either green, or blue, or red,
想要查找 我可以说 colors[colorString]
and I wanted to look it up, I can just say colors, open square bracket, the color string.
它会查找这个字符串
And it will look up that string.
如果没有这样的键 它会返回nil
It would return nil if there's no such key in there.
如果存在 它会返回实际UIColor值
And it will return the value, the actual UI color.
过几张幻灯片我会讲到UIColor
So we're going to talk about UI colors in a couple slides.
这也是访问事物的很酷语法
So this is also really cool UI -- or syntax rather -- for accessing stuff.
这些@方括号 @花括号
These at sign square brackets, at sign curly brace,
@圆括号 是Objective-C中的重大改进
at sign parenthesis -- big improvement to Objective-C.
当然 你也可以看其中有多少对象
Of course, you can see how many objects in there.
你可以用objectForKey来得到它
You can do object for key to get it.
键需要实现hash和isEqual
Key has to implement hash and is equal, right?
这是一张hash表
It's a hash table.
你需要能够为键实现hash 从而能够有效查找
You have to be able to hash the key so we can have an efficient lookup.
但两个键可能hash到相同事物
But then two things might hash to the same thing,
所以你需要isEqual来检验
so you have to have is equal determine whether
hash到相同事物的两个对象是否相等
two objects that hash to the same thing are actually equal.
NSObject对这个的实现很糟糕
NSObject implements this very poorly.
千万别把一个通用对象 或你创建的某种对象的子类
So you would never use a generic object or some subclass of object that you've created.
用作键
You would never use it as a key.
你也许可以使用指针hash
You're probably going to do pointer hashing.
只在对象总是唯一时这才能行
So it would only do it if your objects are always unique.
堆中两个相同对象不会具有不同指针
In the heap there's never two objects that are the same that have different pointers.
字符串在NSDictionary中是很好的键
Strings are excellent keys in NSDictionaries.
我可以说 字典中的键90%的时候都是字符串
And so I would say strings are the key in a dictionary 90 percent of the time.
它们很好
They're very good.
hash很好
They hash really well.
它们很快 对isEqual很有利 等等
They're very fast and do is equal, etc. Okay?
当然 这是不可变的
Of course, immutable, again,
有时我们希望将事物加到字典中
we'd like to sometimes add things to our dictionaries.
所以我们有可变版本的NSMutableDictionary
So we have a mutable version, NSMutable dictionary.
通常用alloc init创建
Usually create it with alloc init.
字典有的它都有
It has all the things of a dictionary,
此外 它还有setObject: forKey:
plus it has set object for key --
来添加一个键值对
that adds a key value pair --
你还可以删掉对象 从另一个字典中加入条目 等等
and you can remove objects, add entries from another dictionary, etc., etc.
循环遍历字典是这样的
Looping through a dictionary looks like this.
使用for id key in 字典
You do for ID key in the dictionary.
对字典使用for in结构 都是遍历键
So basically when you do for in on a dictionary, you're looping through the keys.
当然 循环中间就简单了
Now, of course, inside it's really easy.
你只需要 value等于objectForKey
You just say, "Value equals object for key,"
或者也可以使用方括号表示法来获得值
or even use the square brackets notation to get the value.
这也就循环遍历了值
So you're kind of looping through the values, too,
只要你的hash非常有效
as long as your hashing is efficient,
如果是字符串确实也会很有效
which it is if they're strings. This is [inaudible].
你还可以让字典
It is possible to ask a dictionary,
将所有值作为数组给你
"Give me all your values as an array"?
然后你可以在数组中使用for in循环
And then you could for in through that array.
那是否比这更有效
And whether that's more efficient than doing this probably
取决于字典的规模等等 别太担心这些
depends on the size of your dictionary, etc., etc. Don't worry about it.
这门课中这不要紧
It's never going to be an issue in this class.
我们的字典中不会有成千上万的对象
We're not going to have dictionaries of thousands of objects.
我要讲的下一点不是类 不是语法
Next thing I'm going to talk about is not a class, or syntax,
而是一个短语 属性列表
or whatever; it's a word, a phrase -- property list.
我将定义这个术语
And I'm just going to define this term.
你们需要知道属性列表是什么意思
You need to know what this term means, property list.
属性列表的意思是 集合的集合
A property list means a "collection of collections."
什么是集合
What's a collection?
也就是NSArray 字典 甚至字符串
NSArray, dictionary, even string,
NSData NSNumber
NSData, NSNumber --
这些都是简单的集合
those are all simple collections if you want it think of them
或者可以把它们看成集合的叶节点
that way or they're the leaf nodes of collections.
任意对象图 只要其中只有数组
So if you have any object graph that just has arrays
字典 数字 字符串 日期和数据这些
and dictionaries, numbers, strings, dates, and datas,
那它就是属性列表了
then it's called a "property list."
例如一个字符串数组就是属性列表
So just for an example, if you had an array of strings, that's a property list;
数组的数组
an array of arrays,
而这些数组包含属性列表 那它也是属性列表
and those arrays contain property lists, it's the property list.
任意的图
So any arbitrary graph.
只要其中有这些对象
But as soon as you have any object in there
而且对象属于这些东西或者它们的可变版本
that's not one of these things or they're mutable versions --
可变的这些也是允许的
that's allowed, too; so you can have
例如NSMutableString或NSMutableArray
NSMutableStrings or NSMutableArrays in there --
这就是属性列表了
then it's a property list.
字典是属性列表的条件是 它所有的键
A dictionary is only a property list if all of its keys
及所有值都是属性列表
and all of its values are property lists.
例如键是字符串 值是数组或其它属性列表的字典
So a dictionary that keys are strings,
and values are arrays, or other dictionaries of property lists,
将也是属性列表
that would be a property list.
为什么要定义这个说法呢
Why do we define this term?
因为iOS中有一系列API
Because there's a bunch of API throughout iOS that you're going
将属性列表作为参数
to see that takes a property list as the argument.
但属性列表只是我们定义的一个短语
But property list is only a phrase we define,
其类型可能用的是id
so it's probably going to take an ID. It's going to take an ID.
也可能是NSArray或NSDictionary
It might take an NSArray or an NSDictionary,
取决于API
depending on the API.
不过在说明文档中 它说的基本上是
But it's basically saying in its documentation,
这个的参数是属性列表
"The argument to this is a property list."
如果是数组 那就是属性列表的数组
So even if it's an array, it's got to be an array of property lists.
如果是字典
If it's a dictionary, it's got to be
那就是键和值只有属性列表的字典
a dictionary that has only property lists with keys and values.
如果是id 它将是数组 字典 字符串或数字
If it's an ID, it's got to be an array, or a dictionary, or a string, or number.
这必须是一个属性列表
You know what I mean? It's got to be a property list.
能理解吗
Make sense?
实际上 我要讲一个只作用于属性列表的类
And in fact, I'm going to show you one class that only operates on property lists,
也就是NSUserDefaults
which is NSUserDefaults.
NSUserDefaults是一种共享字典
So NSUserDefaults is this one shared dictionary essentially
这甚至在应用程序启动和退出时仍然持续存在
that persists, even across application launching. Exiting and launching.
它就像是一个永久的NSDictionary
So it's like a permanent NSDictionary kind of.
NSUserDefaults数据库中存储的一切
Everything that's stored in an NSUserDefault database
都必须是一个属性列表
has to be a property list.
不过它并非一个完全的数据库
So it's not a full-on database, though.
它很小
It's pretty small.
性能不是很好
It's not really high performance.
你只能将小东西存放到这里
So you only want to store small things in there.
不要存放大型图片这样的东西
Okay. You don't want to be storing huge images or anything
将它们转化为NSData 然后存储
like that, you know, turning them into NSDatas or something and storing them.
不要这样做
You really don't want to do that.
小字符串 字符串数组 NSNumber
Small strings, and arrays of strings, and NSNumbers,
日期 这些东西是可以的
dates maybe -- those kind of things is okay.
其API
Its API.
要访问它 你要调用NSUserDefaults的这个类方法
To access it, you call this class method on NSUserDefaults
叫standardUserDefaults
called "standard user defaults."
这会给你整个应用中共享的一个实例
And that will give you an instance that is shared across your entire application.
这是全局的
It's like a global.
这种东西只有一个
There's only one of these things.
你将消息发送给它 例如setArray: forKey:
And you send messages to it like this set array for key.
还有setDouble: forKey:
There's also set double for key,
setObject: forKey:
set object for key.
这一对象需要是属性列表
That object would have to be a property list.
这就像是一个字典
So it's kind of like a dictionary
但它还有这些额外方法 如setDouble: forKey:
but it has these extra method like set double for key
这样你就能够存储原始类型到这里
so that you can store primitive types in there
无需先将它们转化为NSNumber
without having to turn them into NSNumbers first.
这里可以说是得到类型检查
You know, it kind of gets the type checking of it
而不只是setObject: forKey:
versus just set object for key where
不知道类型是不是double 等等
it doesn't know whether that's a double or not, etc.
有的这种东西 因为现在我们有了自动装箱
And some of this -- because now we have the autoboxing,
你们知道 @括号这些东西
you know, the at sign parenthesis business --
有的API 我们不再那么需要
some of this API we don't really need that much anymore.
但它仍然在这里 请讲
But it's all still in there. Yeah?
问题是 属性列表这个概念
Yeah. So the question is: Does the property list idea have
是否往下逐步应用到子内容
to cascade down through all of the sub things?
答案是肯定的
And the answer is yes.
要成为属性列表
A property list, for it to be a property list,
整个对象图中的一切都需要是属性列表
everything in the entire object graph has to be a property list.
一直往下
All the way down.
没有例外
No exceptions.
如果你要调用setObject: forKey:这些
And if you were to, for example, call set object for key
你将它往下传递到一个叶节点 它是Card
and you passed it something that somewhere down a leaf node was a card, right,
或某种非属性列表的东西
or some nonproperty list thing,
这个方法会引发异常 说
this method would raise an exception and say,
这不是属性列表 这是在运行时
"That's not a property list," okay, at runtime.
这会让程序崩溃
So it would crash your program.
还要记住一点
The other thing to remember, though,
一旦得到这种standardUserDefaults实例
is once you've gotten this standard user default instance
且你存储了你想存储的
and you've stored what you want,
你需要调用这个synchronize方法来同步
you have to call this method synchronize on the instance.
[NSUserDefaults standardUserDefaults]
So NSUserDefault, standard user default,
synchronize
synchronize.
这是让它永久的东西
That's what makes it permanent.
你写了一些东西 一些批处理 然后同步
So you write a few things, a little batch, and then synchronize.
不要忘记同步
Don't forget to synchronize.
如果你要在这里设置一些东西
If you were to set some things in there
app在同步之前崩溃 它不会得到同步化
and your app crashed before you did the synchronize, it would not get synced.
app重启时 你存入那里的东西会消失
When your app launched again it would be gone, the stuff you put in there.
Foundation的核心部分中 我要讲的最后一点是
The last thing really I'm going to talk about that's kind of in the core part of Foundation
NSRange 也是一种C struct
is NSRange, which is just a C struct.
顾名思义 它描述一个范围
It's exactly what you think: It describes a range.
这可以是字符串的范围 也可以是数组的范围
This might be a range in a string or it could be a range in an array.
基本上是一个开始位置
It's basically a starting location,
也就是NSUInteger location
that's the NSUInteger location
还有长度
and a length --
有多少字符 或数组中有多少项目
how many characters or how many items in the array?
有一个重要的常数叫作NSNotFound
There's an important constant called NSNotFound.
NSNotFound是range中location值
NSNotFound is the value of location in a range
没有被发现 或者无效
that was not found or that is otherwise invalid.
例如 在一个字符串中搜索子字符串
Okay. So it's, like, search for a substring in a string
结果找不到 这就会返回一个range
and it couldn't find it, you're going to get a range back
其位置将是NSNotFound
that the location is going to be NSNotFound.
大家都理解吗
Everyone understand that?
然后还有这个 NSRangePointer
There's also this thing, NSRangePointer.
这其实是一个NSRange
That's basically just an NSRange star.
我讲过 iOS中 我们不会将struct放到堆中
Okay. Now I told you in iOS we don't really put structs in the heap and we don't.
这个NSRangePointer 用于引用调用range
This NSRangePointer is for call by reference ranges.
有些方法会将NSRangePointer作为参数
So some methods will take an NSRangePointer as an argument -- one of its arguments --
这里说的是
and what it's saying there is,
如果你将一个指向range的指针传递给我
"If you pass me a pointer to a range,
我将使用一些信息填充它
I'll fill it in with some information."
这里你几乎总是可以传递null
Almost always you can pass null there
它不会填入任何信息 因为你没有指向一个range
and it won't fill the information in because you won't be pointing to a range.
但这是用于引用 大家都理解引用调用吗
But it's for reference. Everyone know what it means to call by reference?
有问题
Question?
学生：我只是好奇 为什么你用unsigned
> Just out of curiosity, why are you using unsigned
或者说为什么苹果选择对range使用unsigned
or why did Apple choose to use unsigned on its range.
看起来好像不能用负数来表示range
It seems like you can't represent a range over negative numbers.
老师：问题是 为什么苹果选择
> Yeah. So the question is: Why did Apple choose
将location值预设为无符号整数
to make location be an unsigned integer?
换句话说 为什么range只能是正的范围
In other words, why can the range only be a positive range?
我想 主要原因可能在于
And I think the main reason they did that is, you know,
他们是为自己的目的设计NSRange的
they designed NSRange for their own purposes,
例如数组的范围 字符串的范围
like ranges in arrays, ranges in strings.
他们不想像那样表示
They never want to represent that.
而且我敢打赌 NSNotFound要么是最大整数
And I will bet you dollars to doughnuts NSNotFound is either the maximum integer
要么是负数
or it's minus, you know, whatever, negative,
这些有时是一样的
which sometimes are the same thing, right?
计算机科学就是这样
If you know how computer science works,
很多时候 所有二进制数倒过来 这就是-1
a lot of times it's all the bits inverted, that's minus one
这也是范围的最后
that also would be at the end of the range.
我想 这是因为他们不需要其它的
So I think it's just because they didn't need it for anything else and they wanted
他们希望自己的API尽可能简洁明了
to make their API clearer possibly.
我不知道
I don't know.
我从未在苹果干过 所以我不知道他们为什么那么做
I don't work at Apple -- never did -- so I don't really know why they did that.
以上就是Foundation方面 我要讲的所有内容了
Okay. So that's really kind of it for the Foundational stuff.
我还会讲到Foundation中的一些类
I am going to talk about some more classes in Foundation.
但首先 我先转换一下主题 讨论UIKit中的一些类
But first we're going to take a little detour and talk about a couple classes in UIkit.
也就是颜色和字体
And those are colors and fonts.
UIColor是超级简单的类 表示颜色
All right. So UIColor, super simple class, represents a color.
颜色可以用很多方式表示
The color can be represented in so many different ways,
包括RGB 即红绿蓝
RGB -- red, green, blue, right?
HSB 即色调 饱和度 亮度
HSB, that's hue, saturation, and brightness.
它甚至可以是一个样式
It could even be a pattern.
你可以让颜色是一个UIImage样式
Okay. So you can have a color that is a UI image pattern in there.
当你用那个颜色绘图时 它会用那个样式
And when you draw with that color, it will draw with the pattern.
颜色 超级强大 但API很简单明了
So color, super powerful but nice and simple API.
颜色还可以有alpha
Colors can also have alpha.
多少人不知道alpha是什么
Okay. How many people in here do not know what alpha is?
没听过alpha这个词
Never heard the phrase "alpha"?
大家都知道alpha是什么
So everybody knows what alpha is.
它是第一个希腊字母
Okay. So that's a first.
alpha在计算机图形中表示透明度
So alpha, which in computer graphics is how transparent it
1表示完全不透明 0表示完全透明
is -- one being fully opaque and zero being fully transparent.
你可以创建部分透明的颜色
You can create colors that are partially transparent.
用它们绘图时 你会看到它们是如何填充的
And then if you draw with them, you'll be able to see behind where you filled in.
颜色很酷
So colors are really cool.
颜色有一些标准的
There's a handful of kind of standard colors --
绿色 红色 紫色 等等
the green color, red color, purple color, whatever.
你可以在说明文档中找到这些
You can look in its documentation to find those.
它们只不过是类方法
They're just class method.
然后还有一些方法 像lightTextColor
There's also a few methods in there like the light text color,
这是为浅色文本 禁用文本这些准备的灰色阴影
which is the shade of gray for light text, disabled text, or whatever.
这些你们都可以看看
So you can look at all that.
颜色很简单
So colors are simple.
字体 没这么简单
Fonts, not so simple.
iOS7中 将字体设置正确是非常重要的
Now, fonts in iOS 7 are incredibly important to get right.
iOS7的UI设计 很大一部分都取决于字体选择
A huge percentage of good iOS 7 UI design is picking the right fronts,
使用方式正确 以及屏幕排列美观
and using fonts in the right way, arranging fonts on screen in a nice way.
超级重要
Super important.
所以iOS7中有很多新支持
So there's a lot of support in iOS 7 that's new
帮助我们更容易将字体设置正确
that is basically about making it easy to do the right thing with fonts.
这里我列出了一些iOS7 app的例子
So I put up some examples of some iOS 7 apps here.
可以看到所有这些例子中 字体具有怎样的重要作用
And you can see how front and center fonts are on all these things.
如果字体很丑 例如没有用粗体
If you had ugly fonts here or you didn't have bold,
或者字体之间揉在一起
or you had, you know, fronts that were too smashed together
或很难读 或颜色错误
or hard to read or the wrong color,
这些UI将会很难辨识
these UIs would be, you know, impossible to decipher or very difficult to decipher here.
所以 颜色 背景颜色 还有字体大小
So color, and background colors, and, you know, the size of fonts,
所有这些在应用中都至关重要
and all these things are all critically important in all of these applications.
我将简单讲一下如何处理这些
So we're going to talk a little bit about how to deal
以及iOS7中所有这些是如何做到的
with this and what's in there for iOS 7 to make this happen.
很不幸 我课上没有足够时间详细讲解所有这些
Unfortunately, I don't have enough time in lecture in general to go through all of this.
我们会在关于UI的课堂和演示中
I'll kind of distribute little bits of wisdom about it as we go
零星讲到其中一些内容
through various UIs in lecture, and demos, and things like that.
今天我将大致介绍一下基础
What I'm going to try and give you today is just the basis
告诉你们如何将文字呈现在屏幕上
for how we present text on screen.
这方面有哪些基本内容
What the primitives are for that
如何正确使用并保持一致
and how we do it in the right way so that we get consistency.
注意 所有这些app中
See, the one thing about all these apps --
都有粗体 以及可以点击的字体
do you see how the bold font, and the fonts you can click on,
还有小的子标题字体
and the kind of little subheading fonts,
它们都是相关的字体 相同种类 也许 也许不是
they're all related fonts, same family -- maybe, maybe not.
但它们是相关的
But they're related.
大小相同
They're the same sizes.
看起来一样 因此所有app都有类似的外观
They look the same. So all the apps kind of have a similar look.
因为它们的字体使用都很合适
That's because they're all using fonts properly.
我来讲讲字体
So let's talk about fonts.
关于字体要了解的最重要一点是
The most important thing to understand about fonts is
如果你在展示用户内容 也就是用户的信息
that if you're displaying user content -- okay, that the user's information.
在日历中 也就是预约 日期
So in the calendar that's the appointments, and the days
星期几 月份 所有这些
of the week, and the month, and all those things.
在天气中 则是温度 城市名等等
In the weather it's the temperature, and the name of the city, and things like that.
在计时应用中 则是时钟所在城市
In the timer app it's the city that the clock is in.
如果是用户内容
So if it's user content --
也就是说 不是按钮上的文字
in other words, it's not the text on a button.
按钮上的文字便于用户点击 如编辑等等
It's not a text on a button that user's clicking like edit or something like that.
那么你就需要使用首选字体 所谓的首选字体
Then you want to use a preferred font, what's called a "preferred font."
所以你需要这种很重要的方法
And so you want this incredibly important method.
UIFont中如果你只学一种方法
If you only learn one method in all of UI font,
那肯定就是这种iOS7方法
it's this iOS 7 method
叫作preferredFontForTextStyle
called "preferred font for text style."
文本样式参数是一个字符串
The text style argument is a string.
你将使用一个常数
You use a constant
这可以在UIFontDescriptor中查到
that you're going to look up in UI font descriptor, actually.
查看UIFont 四处点一下 你可以找到它
If you go through UI font, you can link click through and find it.
这里有体样式
And so there's the body style.
这是体中的文字 体也就是显示的主要部分
So that's text that's in the body, the main part of what's being displayed.
例如在预约中 这将是…
So like, in an appointment that would be --
在日历中
like in a calendar item
这将是关于某预约时实际将会发生什么的信息
that would be the actual information about what's going to happen at that appointment.
然后还有标题样式
And then there's a headline style.
这显然用于标题
So that would be, obviously, a header.
还有脚注 解说文字 例如图像上的解说文字 等等
There's footnotes, captions, like a caption on an image, things like that.
这些样式总共有大概八个
There's about, I think, eight or so of these.
你们应该熟悉
And you should familiarize yourself
什么语义环境下应该使用什么样式
with what circumstances semantically those things should be used in.
你们在app中使用字体时 应该从这些里面选择
And then when you want a font in your app, you should be using one of these.
用于用户内容
For user content.
还有系统字体
There's also system fonts.
这些是按钮上的字体
These are what goes on buttons.
不要在用户内容中使用系统字体
Don't use the system fonts for user content.
有时 在按钮上使用首选字体是可以的
Sometimes it's okay to use a preferred font on a button.
这取决于按钮的标题是否会变化
It depends on whether the title of the button might change,
取决于用户内容
depending on user's, you know, content.
这是按钮上的用户内容
Basically it's the user's content on a button.
这没问题
That would be okay.
但一般不要对用户内容使用系统字体
But you generally wouldn't want to use system fonts for user's content.
这是按钮上用的字体 你们知道 就是这样
So this is what's on a button, what's -- you know, that kind of thing.
UIFontDescriptor
UI font descriptor.
我在发布的幻灯片中额外加了一些
I put some extra slides in what I posted
关于UIFontDescriptor的内容
that talks more about UI font descriptor.
这里我不打算细讲
I'm not going to go through them here.
你们可以自己看一下
You can look through them, just kind of get a little bit
从而对UIFontDescriptor有一定了解
of a hint for UI font descriptor.
关于这个我就想说一点
But the bottom line is:
字体不是计算机程序员设计的 而是艺术家设计的
Fonts are designed not by computer programmers but by artists.
艺术家设计字体 也许设计已经有数百年历史了
Artists design fonts, and they've been designing them for hundreds of years.
也许有几百年历史了 这是印刷出版刚兴起的时候
Yeah, probably couple hundred years since the ledgers, since presses were made.
古腾堡是什么时候我不大确定
I don't know when Gutenberg was exactly.
这考了考我的历史
Testing my history here.
但这些设计
But those were designed.
是很久以前雕刻在铅块上使用的
You know, back then you actually etched on pieces of lead or whatever.
而现在 设计是在PhotoShop或Illustrator
Now they're designed in, you know, PhotoShop or Illustrator probably type, you know,
或别的什么矢量图形设计工具上
vector graphics designing tools.
这个的问题是
And the problem with that is
它们并不一定满足我们计算机科学家所想要的
that they don't fit what we computer scientists want,
也就是 我们想要这种字体的粗体版本
which is we want the bold version of this font,
我们想要斜体 我们想要细体
we want the italic version, we want the narrow version.
除非字体设计者实际设计了粗体或斜体
Okay. Unless the font designer actually designs a bold font or an italic font
一般而言我们没有这些
[inaudible], we don't get it. We don't get one of those.
我们可以尝试将它拉粗一些
We could try and somehow scrunch it up to look more bold,
但这通常看起来很糟糕
but that usually looks, like, bad.
看起来不会好
That does not look good.
UIFontDescriptor是iOS7中的新特性
So UI font descriptor's new in iOS 7.
它会尝试将类别施加在未分类化的字体上
It attempts to put categories on fonts that defy categorization.
UIFontDescriptor在这方面有很多知识
So the UI font descriptor has a lot of knowledge in it
关于某字体是否有黑体版本
about faces and is there a bold version of this,
有没有细体 有没有斜体
is there a condensed version, is there an italic version?
它会将此映射到我们计算机科学家希望处理的事物上
And so it maps that into something we, as computer scientists, want to do
因为我们希望将黑体的事物显示在屏幕上
because we want to put something in bold on the screen.
UIFontDescriptor就是这样了
So that's what UI font descriptor is all about.
哪怕大小 也通常设计到字体中
Even size, by the way, is designed into a font often.
字体设计者对较大S的设计中 会有更多曲线
A designer of a font will design a larger S with a little more curve here and there
而较小S则不是这样
than a smaller S. Okay?
大小并不只是矢量图形的放大和缩小
Size is not just a matter of vector graphic zooming in and out --
有时 它会取决于字体
sometimes, it depends on the font.
你们可以看看幻灯片 看具体情况是怎样的
So anyway, look at that, at slides that are in there to try and figure that out.
作业中没有任何内容涉及到UIFontDescriptor
There's nothing you will have to do in your homeworks that is font descriptor.
你们可能需要考虑字体 但UIFontDescriptor不需要
You might have to do fonts but not font descriptors, I don't think.
有兴趣的话 你们可以做一些更进阶的东西
You might want to if you want to do some advanced stuff.
理解了这些
So understand, though, that,
当你使用UIFontDescriptor
yeah, when you do a font descriptor and you
要它给你字体相应的粗体
ask it for a bold version of a font,
你可能得不到粗体
you might not get a bold version.
你会得到它能给出的最接近的东西
You'll get the best thing it can come up with,
但也许看起来并非粗体
but it might not actually look bold,
取决于是什么字体 它有没有相应的粗体 等等
depending on what font it is and whether it has a bold, etc.
下面我们来谈 文本在屏幕上的效果
So now let's talk about how text looks on screen.
字体是文本屏幕效果的一个重要部分
Well, the font is a big part of how text looks on screen.
取决于你选择什么字体
Depending on which font you pick, that's going
这会很大程度上决定效果
to determine a lot of what it looks like.
但还有很多其它因素
But there's a lot of other things
会决定字体在屏幕上的效果
that determine what a font looks like on screen.
例如 文本有没有下划线
For example, is the thing underlined?
是不是空心字体
Is it outlined?
字体的外边缘有多强的描边
How strongly stroked is the outer edge of the font?
这些都独立于字体
Those things are all kind of independent of the font.
这些可以应用到任何字体
You can apply these things to any font.
所以 Foundation中有一个新类你们会学到
So there's a new class that you're going to learn that's in Foundation
叫NSAttributedString
called NSAttributedString.
NSAttributedString非常非常简单
And an NSAttributedString, very, very simple.
它很像… 它不是NSString 但它很像NSString
It's like -- it is not an NSString -- but it's like an NSString
每个字符都有一个属性字典
where every character has a dictionary of attributes.
这些属性诸如下划线 描边宽度 字体等等
And those attributes are like underlined, or stroke width, font, etc. Okay?
我说它很像NSString是因为 它不是NSString的子类
Now, the reason I say it's like NSString -- it's not a subclass of NSString.
你不能将字符串消息发送给它
You cannot send it string messages.
这是一个很重大的限制
So that seems like a significant restriction. And it is,
等下我们会谈到如何处理它
and we'll talk about how we're going to deal with that in a second.
设置属性可以仅仅通过调用…
You set the attributes simply by calling --
抱歉 这是NSAttributedString
sorry, this is NSAttributedString.
它是不可变的 不可修改
It's immutable -- immutable -- not modifiable.
所以NSAttributedString的属性无法设置
So you cannot set the attributes of an NSAttributedString.
还有可变的带属性字符串 等下我会讲到
There is a mutable attributed string; we'll talk about that in a second.
获得属性可以通过调用attributesAtIndex:
So you get the attributes by calling attributes at index.
它会返回一个字典给你
And it will return you a dictionary
包含这一下标处字符的所有属性
with all the attributes for the character at that index.
而这个NSRangePointer
And that NSRangePointer,
如果你传递一个指针给一个range struct
if you pass it a pointer to a range struct,
它会用"多少字符具有完全相同的属性"来填充它
it will fill it in with "How many characters have the exact same attributes?"
它这里是在明确你想要属性的位置
So it's basically you specify the location that you want the attributes
如果很多字符具有这种属性
and if a whole bunch of characters have those exact same attributes,
它会返回这个范围 如果你要求的话
it will return that range if you ask it.
能理解吗 这个范围是什么
Does that make sense, what that range is?
它告诉你 多少字符具有
It's basically just telling you how many characters have the
你要询问的字符处的属性
attributes you asked for at that character.
如果你不关心 你可以传递null
You can pass null if you don't care and just want
只想知道那个字符的属性
to know the attributes of that character.
NSAttributedString不是字符串
So NSAttributedString is not a string.
但我们希望做类似字符串的事情
But we want to do string-like things.
我们希望搜索其它子字符串 做这类能对字符串做的事情
We want to search for other substrings and things like that, that we do on a string.
所以NSAttributedString中有一个方法
So there's a method in NSAttributedString --
它很重要 叫作string
really important one -- called "string."
这会返回一个NSString 你可以进行搜索
And this will return an NSString that you can then search in
做所有能对字符串做的事
or do all the string things you want.
例如 如果你想搜索
For example, if we wanted to search,
NSString中有个方法叫rangeOfString
there's a method in NSString called "range of string,"
它会返回一个NSRange 告诉你
which returns an NSRange that tells you
字符串中子字符串在哪
where a substring is in a string.
我们可以说 我们有一个带属性字符串
And so we can just say we have an attributed string lying
我们要找某个子字符串
around and we're looking for some substring;
我们可以说
we just say
[attributedString string] rangeOfString:substring
attributed string string, range of string string,
返回的将是范围
and we'll get the range back.
这个string方法保证能具有高性能
Now, that string method is guaranteed to be very high performance
因为你会一直做这个
because you're doing this all the time.
你希望像字符串那样处理NSAttributedString
You want to look at the NSAttributedString like a string.
它是高性能的
So it's high performance.
但是 它又是容易丢失的
However, it's also volatile.
结果 这个返回的指针可能指向
The bottom line is this thing is probably returning you a pointer
那个NSAttributedString的内部数据结构
to that NSAttributedStrings' internal data structure,
或它的某一部分 这之类
or some parts of it, or something.
你不知道具体是什么
You don't really know what it is.
你知道返回的是一个NSString 但是…
You know whatever it returns is an NSString. But
如果你想保留这个 不仅用于你所调用的地方
so if you want to keep that thing around for more than just right there where you call it,
你可以复制一份
make a copy of it.
这样你就有了NSString的一个副本 可以存储下来
Then you have a copy of the NSString. You can hold onto it.
你几乎从来不需要这样做 因为
You almost never need to do that because you're almost
你基本总会在此时此地处理字符串
always operating on the string right there in place like this --
字符串的范围
a range of string.
你尝试得到它
You're just trying to get it.
这是字符串 NSString中很重要的属性
So that's string. Very important property in NSString.
还有一个可变版本
So there is a mutable one.
可变版本继承自不可变的带属性字符串
And mutable one, it does inherit from the nonmutable attributed string.
但它不是NSString 或NSMutableString
But it's not an NSString or an NSMutableString.
它是一种NSAttributedString
It's an NSAttributedString.
它添加了增加属性和设置属性方法
And it adds these methods to add attributes and set attributes
在带属性字符串中的各种范围内
at various ranges inside the attributed string.
这很容易理解
Exactly what you would think.
几张幻灯片以后 我会讲到这些字典中都有什么
And we're going to talk about what's in these dictionaries in a couple slides.
如果想要修改可变带属性字符串中的字符该怎么做
Now, what if you want to modify the characters in a mutable attributed string?
同带属性字符串一样
Exact same thing as the attributed string.
当你考虑字符时 你可以调用mutableString方法
When you want to look at the characters, you call this method mutable string.
它会返回一个NSMutableString
And it will return an NSMutableString.
信不信由你 如果你修改这个可变字符串
And believe it or not, if you modify that mutable string
回到可变带属性字符串 其属性会追踪你的变化
that you get back, the mutable attributed string, its attributes will track your changes.
例如 如果你插入一些文本 新文本将获得
So like, if you insert some text, the new text will get the attributes
插入处字符的属性
of the character right where you inserted it.
如果你将字符从可变字符串中删除
If you delete characters out of that mutable string,
那么在可变带属性字符串中 那些字符属性也会消失
then the mutable attributed string, those character attributes will just go away.
明白吗
Make sense?
这些类
So these classes --
NSMutableString和NSMutableAttributedString
NSMutableString and NSMutableAttributedString --
相互联系起来 关系就像NSAttributedString
are in bed with each other, just like NSAttributedString
和NSString之间一样
and NSString are in bed with each other.
我不知道苹果是怎么做到的
I don't know how they did it at Apple,
不过这很棒 因为
but it's really nice because it makes it really easy
字符和带属性字符串中的属性都很容易操作
to manipulate both the characters and the attributes in an attributed string.
好 那这些属性字典中都有些什么属性呢
Okay. So what kind of attributes are in those attributes dictionaries?
一个重要的是字体
One of the big ones is the font.
这是一个字典
So this is a dictionary.
字体的键是NSFontAttributeName
The key for the font is NSFontAttributeName.
你们可以去查下这些键
And you can look up these keys by going and looking --
NSAttributedString在说明文档中有一个链接
if you look up NSAttributedString in the documentation, there's a link there,
也就是NSAttributedString的UIKit增添部分
which is UIkit additions to NSAttributedString,
我要讲的所有键都在这里有
and all the keys that I'm going to talk about are there.
其中一个键就是NSFontAttributeName
And one of the keys is NSFontAttributeName.
其值是UIFont
And the value of that is a UIFont.
这就是获得特定样式首选字体的地方
So this is where you would get a preferred font of a certain style,
例如这里是标题
like a headline, let's say, in this case.
如果我的字典中只有这个
So if I had a dictionary that just had this in there --
没有别的 默认文本颜色是黑色
nothing else -- the default text color is black.
也许我的A会是这样的
Probably my letter A would like look that.
如果我将这个键值对加到我的字典呢
What if I added this key value pair to my dictionary?
NSForegroundColorAttributeName :
NS Foreground Color Attribute Name,
[UIColor blueColor]
UIColor, blue color. So
这里的键是NSForegroundColorAttributeName
here the key is this foreground color attribute name;
值是UIColor
the value is a UIColor.
这将它换成蓝色
So that changed it to blue.
我还可以将它换成绿色
Okay. And I could change it to green if I wanted to.
创建具有颜色文本的带属性字符串时要小心
Be a little bit careful when you create an attributed string that has colored text
因为在iOS7中 文本颜色有时是一个指示器
because in iOS 7 the color of text sometimes is an indicator
告诉终端用户他们能够触摸什么
to the end user what they can touch.
iOS的app中有一个颜色主题 默认是蓝色
And so if -- turns out apps in iOS kind of have a color theme. The default is blue.
所以Machismo的按钮我们用的是蓝色
That's why on Machismo buttons that we make will be blue.
不过也可以是别的颜色 例如橙色
But they can be different colors like orange.
这取决于你想要怎样的色彩
It depends on what tint you want your thing to be.
这些颜色通常就是暗示能够触击
But whatever your color is of your app, that color you can usually tap on.
这是按钮上文本的颜色 用于链接的文字的颜色
Okay. That's the color of text on buttons, text at the top of the screen to navigate places.
所以你要小心 不要将不能触击的文本设置为这种颜色
So be careful not to set anything else to be that color unless you can tap on it.
颜色上你需要很小心
Be real careful with color.
还有描边宽度属性 以及描边颜色
There's also stroke width attribute and stroke color.
宽度属性 注意这个 因为以后在作业中
The width attribute -- and pay attention to this because you'll need this probably
你们可能会需要 这是一个NSNumber
for your homework -- it's an NSNumber.
如果是负NSNumber 那就意味着填充字形
If it's a negative NSNumber, then that means fill glyph,
这里也就是填充A 并描边
you know, the A fill it, and stroke around the edge.
如果是正数 那就意味着只描边
If it's a positive number, it means just do the stroke around the edge
而中间则是透明的
and the middle is transparent.
看看还有什么
What else can we have?
下划线样式属性名
Underline style attribute name.
这是一个NSNumber 它具有一个enum
So that's an NSNumber that has an enum,
有NSUnderlineStyleSingle或Double
one of NS style underline style single or double.
还有NSUnderlineStyleNone
Or there's also NS underline style none.
表示没有下划线
That would be no underlining.
然后还有背景颜色
There's also background color.
这里是想告诉你们 这是可以的
So here just to show you this is possible,
我将这个字形的背景设为了透明黄色
I set the background of this glyph to be a transparent yellow.
它是透明度为30%的黄色
It's thirty percent visible, thirty percent towards opaque yellow.
所以这里可以看到黑板的颜色
So you see how you can see the chalkboard shown through there?
我不知道iTunes U视频中显得得如何 你们应该能够看得出
I don't know if that will show up on iTunes U. But here hopefully you can see --
我可以看到黄色背景后的东西
I can see through that yellow background.
你们在作业中 也应该
In your homework, you might want to think
尝试用一下透明色
about using transparent colors somewhere else.
不是字符背景 而是填充颜色这些
Okay. Not the background of a character or maybe the fill color or something.
不管怎样
Anyway, okay.
透明色很好
So transparent color's good.
但愿你们都感受到了
Okay. So hopefully you're all getting a feel, then,
我们是如何构建这个字典的
for how we build this dictionary.
我们只需要设置字符的属性
Okay. All we need to do is set the attributes of the characters
设置为我们所希望设定的这一系列属性
that we want to have this particular set of attributes.
我们在哪使用带属性字符串呢
So where do we use attributed strings?
我可以创建一个带属性字符串
So I can create an attributed string.
它有所有这些属性
It's got all these attributes.
在哪使用它呢
Okay. Where do I use it?
我可以在按钮上使用它
Well, I can use it in a button.
我可以设置按钮的标题为带属性字符串
Okay. I can set the title of a button to be an attributed string.
这对你们的作业可能会有好处
That might be useful for your homework.
我们可以创建一个具有带属性字符串的UILabel
We can create a UI label that has an attributed string.
还有一个很重要的类 也许下次我会讲到
And a very important class, which I'm probably going to talk about next time,
也就是UITextView
which is UITextView.
UITextView类似于UILabel
UITextView is like a UILabel,
但它可编辑 可选择 可滚动等等
but it's editable, selectable, scrollable, etc. Okay?
我们来看一下按钮
So let's talk about button.
实际上 我不打算详细讲按钮
Actually, I'm not going to talk about button,
我只想说 它对你们的作业很重要
except for to say it's important for your homework.
它有一个方法setAttributedTitle:
It just has a method -- set attributed title --
就像setTitle: forState:一样
just like it has set title for a state,
这里有setAttributedTitle: forState:
it has set attributed title for state.
你会用到这个
And you're going to want to use that.
还有可能直接在屏幕上绘制字符串
It's also possible to draw strings directly on screen.
不过我们还没讨论到直接在屏幕上绘制
But we haven't talked about drawing on screen directly yet.
这部分内容我们将推迟到下周
So we'll postpone until we talk about that next week.
不过我们是能够直接在屏幕上绘制带属性字符串的
But we will be able to draw attributed strings on screens directly,
就像我们能够直接在屏幕上绘制直线这些一样
just like we can draw lines and things like that directly on screen.
UILabel有一个属性
UILabel has a property,
它是一个NSAttributedString 叫作
it's an NSAttributedString called
attributedText
"attributed text."
就像文本标签 这是一个NSString
It's just like the text label, which is an NSString,
我们已经使用过这个
which we've already used in this class,
例如分数标签和翻牌计数标签
we like the score label and the flips label.
我们设置了文本属性
We set the text property.
这里有一个带属性的文本属性
So there's an attributed text property.
你通过NSAttributedString 而非NSString设置属性
And you just set the property via an NSAttributedString instead of an NSString.
就是这样了
And that's it.
很不幸 它是只读的
Unfortunately, it's read-only.
它是不可变的
Okay. It's immutable.
该属性不是NSMutableAttributedString
That property you see is not an NS Mutable Attributed String;
它只是NSAttributedString
it's an NSAttributedString.
如果你希望改变UILabel上的带属性文本
So if you want to change the attributed text that's on a UILabel,
你需要获取标签 复制它得到一个可变副本
you have to get the label, make a mutable copy of it,
按要求修改它 再将它放回去
modify it however you want, and put it back.
如果你有一个已有标签
Okay. That's if you have an existing label and you want
你想把它变成蓝色 而非绿色 诸如此类
to make it be blue instead of green or something like that.
你需要获取它 创建一个可变副本
You have to get it, create a mutable copy,
修改属性 再将它放回去
modify the attributes, put it back.
标签上 你不需要经常这样做
You don't need to do this very often on labels.
标签上不会经常出现带属性文本
Labels don't really have attributed text on them that much.
也许是设置颜色
Maybe to set the color.
也许 如果有一些专门标签
Possibly if they're specialty labels that are kind
用于指定并非正常文本的东西
of specifying something that's not just normal text.
所以说 这对UILabel并不那么普遍
So it's not that common to do UILabel.
今天我要讲的也就这些了
So that's all I'm going to cover for today, I think.
周五有一堂讨论课
We do have a Friday section.
时间在我讲课的时候得到了确认
The time is being confirmed to me probably as I speak right now.
我会发布在Piazza上
I will post that for you on Piazza.
时间是周五
It's on Friday.
我记得应该是周五1点在102室
I believe it's going to be at 1:00 o'clock on Friday in 102. Okay, unit 102.
不过不要以我为准 以Piazza为准
But don't hold me to that yet. Look at Piazza.
我们会谈到调试
We're going to be talking about debugging.
iOS7有一些新的调试内容 它们非常酷
There are some new debugging things for iOS 7 that are pretty cool.
我们会讲到一些
We'll get to a couple of them.
我还将讲到Xcode的一些要诀和技巧
And we're also going to talk about Xcode tips and tricks.
Command键组合非常有价值
So command key combinations that are really valuable to have,
如何设置偏好 让你的体验更好一些
how to set some preferences up to make your experience a little nicer.
这些都是可选的 不要求大家一定到课
So it's totally optional. You don't need to go there.
很多人很了解Xcode
A lot of you know Xcode.
也很熟悉调试 至少在其它语言中
You're probably used to debugging, at least in other languages.
所以 就算没上 也不是世界末日
So, you know, if you miss it, it's not going to be the end the world.
不过这可能会有价值
But it might be valuable.
下周一我将讲到UITextView
Next Monday I'm going to talk about UITextView
它是NSMutableAttributedString的最重要使用者
since it's the most important user of NS Mutable Attributed String.
然后我将讲到来自MVC的电台
And then I'm also going to talk about the radio station from MVC.
记得MVC模型吗
Remember that MVC model?
我讲过 有时通信可以通过电台的广播来进行
I told you that sometimes communication happens by radio station, where you broadcast
其它对象收听 我们会讲到这个
and some other objects tune in. We're going to talk about doing that.
然后我有一个大demo 演示带属性字符串
And then I have a big demo that does attributed strings,
文本视图等等所有这些
and text views, and all that stuff.
然后我们将开始谈到视图控制器生命周期
And then we're going to go start talking about the view controller lifecycle,
也就是你的视图控制器
okay, which is your view controller.
首先开始存在
It comes into existence.
它会发生一些事情
Things happen to it.
例如显示在屏幕上 从屏幕上消失 改变大小 等等
It appears on screen and goes off screen, changes size, things like that.
然后它消失
And then it goes away.
从屏幕消失 甚至完全消失
Okay. It goes off screen and maybe even disappears.
这个发生的过程中 你会得到系统的通知
And as all that happens, you get notified by the system.
你需要知道 什么时候获得通知 怎么做
And it's important to know when you're going to get notified and what to do
这些通知在哪
where in terms of that notification.
我们会在周一谈到这些 视图控制器生命周期
So we'll be talking about that on Monday, view controller lifecycle.
它对你们下次作业至关重要
Super important one for your next homework.
你们下次作业也许是周一布置 也许是下周三布置
Your next homework might go out on Monday; might go out on next Wednesday.
我们现在还不确定
I'm not quite sure yet.
反正都是一周后交
But in case, it will be due a week later.
就这些了
So that's it.
有问题的可以来提
And if you have any questions, I'll be here.
下次再见
And I'll see you next time.
更多内容 请访问我校官网stanford.edu
> For more, please visit us at Stanford.edu.